<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Romes ruin or A treatise of the certaine destruction of Rome and of Antichrist before the ende of the world Wherein is cleerely manifested out of the Holy Scriptures, conferred with the historie of the Papacie, that he hath but a short time. A worke published to strengthen the faith of such as suffer vnder him. By I.P.</title>
            <author>I. P., fl. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855295</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Romes ruin or A treatise of the certaine destruction of Rome and of Antichrist before the ende of the world Wherein is cleerely manifested out of the Holy Scriptures, conferred with the historie of the Papacie, that he hath but a short time. A worke published to strengthen the faith of such as suffer vnder him. By I.P.</title>
                  <author>I. P., fl. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed [abroad] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXIX. [1629]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20781:1"/>
            <p>ROMES RVIN. OR A TREATISE Of the certaine Deſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> and of Antichriſt before the ende of the World. <hi>WHEREIN IS CLEERELY Manifeſted out of the Holy Scriptures, Conferred with the Historie of the Papacie, that he hath but a ſhort time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A worke publiſhed to ſtrengthen the faith of ſuch as ſuffer vnder him.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 137.8.</bibl>
               <p>O Daughter of Babylon, who art to be destroyed: Happie ſhall he be that rewardeth thee as thou hast ſerued vs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, M.DC.XXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20781:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20781:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath neuer beene any part of my intent, Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in the writing or publiſhing of this litle Treatiſe, to take on me after the manner of ſome preciſely to finde out, and peremptorily to ſet downe the verrie yeare wherein <hi>Rome</hi> or Antichriſt ſhall be deſtroyed, or to name the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Prince</hi> or Kingdom, whoſe Kinge ſhall be Generall at the Seidge, and ruin of that <hi>Babylon;</hi> the worke it ſelfe will both quit me of ſuch fond preſumptions, and witneſſe that my aime herein is not to get a vaine glorious name of knowledge in ſuch mysteries; nor to fill the world with ſtronge deluſions, opinions and expectations of improbable alterations; but rather for the honour of Almightie God (now in theeſe wauering and fainting times, wherein <hi>mens hearts faile them for feare,</hi> that the preuailing aduerſaries will ſubdue all to Romiſh obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) to winne men to an aſſured confidence in his promiſed meraies of deliuerance; and what they can, to ſerue and waite on his almightie power, and prouidence with ſuch iust meanes, as he hath appointed therevnto; eſpetially now when they ſhall ſee it manifested by thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable testimonies, the propheſies of holy Scripture, and Hiſtories of the Papacie anſwering them, that <hi>Romes Ruin</hi> muſt needes be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching, and can not chooſe but fall out within a few yeares of this preſent: which is ſufficient for me to haue manifested. As for thoſe who profeſſe themſelues Protestants, and yet in theeſe dangerous times are ſo far from affecting or approuing ſuch knowledge, that on the contrarie they doubt whether it be lawfull and proffitable, to looke into theeſe Propheſies for the time and meanes of deliuerance, and ouerthrow of the aduerſaries; whether ſuch looking be not rather curioſity, folly, &amp; preſumption; whether courſes of iuſtice and warres vndertaken for the defence of the Gospell and ouerthrow of Poperie, and the Supporters thereof, be lawfull or neceſſary; whether a peace with them all is not much rather to be wiſhed; and whether it be not much better that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants &amp; Papiſts ſhould firſt ioyne together againſt theire co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie the <hi>Turke:</hi> In theeſe and the like ſcruples, ſuch as are not partiall and obſtinate, may by a thorow reading of this ſmall booke receiue compotent ſatisfaction.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20781:3"/>
            <p>In the meane time, I anſwer noe more heere to theire ſuggeſtions, then this, 1. That noe man can more deteſt, then I doe, all warres vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for deſire of ſpoile, territories &amp; Empire, all not worth the life blood of one Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; knowing that the miſeries, that euer follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are great &amp; lamentable; that peace &amp; mercie can neuer be ſufficiently admired &amp; extended; but not toward <hi>Amalek</hi> or <hi>Romiſh Babel</hi> and her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, becauſe theire deſtructions are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in holy Scriptures, and he is counted <hi>happie</hi> that ſhall <hi>ſerue her</hi> as ſhe hath <hi>ſerued</hi> others. 2. That it was lawfull, proffitable, and comfortable for the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time of the captiuity,
<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>9.2.</hi>
               </note> to looke, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did, after the time and meanes of deliuerance, espetially when the ſeauentie yeares were almoſt out; to looke alſo into the Propheſie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> for the laſt period of thoſe ſeuerall Beaſts, &amp; hornes mentioned Dan. 7. &amp; chap. 8. espetially for deliuerance from <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> that litle <hi>horne</hi> chap. 8.9. for the time and ende of the deſolation he cauſeth, expreſly noted verſ. 13.14. and for the comming and ſaluation of Chriſt, and other occurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſignified in thoſe propheticall weekes of <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 9. Euen as old <hi>Simeon waited for the conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. <hi>2.</hi> Mark. <hi>15.43</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Ioſeph of Arimathea</hi> is ſaide to haue <hi>waited for the Kingdom of God:</hi> and that therefore, it is as lawfull now for all true Chriſtians, beholding the deſolations that Antichriſt, and his Adherents make, to looke into the propheſies of holy Scripture for the time and meanes of the deliuerance, there promiſed, eſpetially ſeeing that when <hi>Rome</hi> the cauſe of theeſe miſeries is deſtroied,
<note place="margin">Reu. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> it is ſaide, <hi>Alleluia: for the Lord God omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent raigneth:</hi> whereas, before that, ſhe raigned in matters of faith and ſaluation,
<note place="margin">Reu. <hi>17.18.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>ouer the Kings of the earth.</hi> But then <hi>Gods Kingdom commeth:</hi> this wee are taught to <hi>pray</hi> for, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. <hi>6.33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſeeke.</hi> And therefore when after the writing of this ſmall booke, I had kept it a longe time, without imparting the ſight of it to any man, I thought I could now doe noe leſſe then publiſh it, with ſome few additions, and that indeede, that ſuch as ſee the miſeries of the Church, and ſeeke to redreſſe them, may ſtriue to doe it by that right meanes which God hath preſcribed, and not by any contrarie to that which God, <hi>that changeth not,</hi> hath in his <hi>Holy Word</hi> reuealed to be the only ſure remedie, and that by which he hath determined to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme his Church from Antichristian perſecution, bondage and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20781:3"/>
            <head>ROMES RVIN. OR <hi>A Treatiſe of the certaine deſtruction of</hi> Rome <hi>and of Antichrist before the ende of the VVorld.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſay nothing of theire opinions in this point, who are either Popiſh or newters, or lukewarm, or temporiſers, or worldlings, or which are afraid of the Popiſh armies; becauſe euery wiſe man will eaſely conceiue that theire verdict in this matter muſt needes be partiall, as proceeding from ſiniſter reſpects, or theire owne perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſts: I readily acknowledge that there are many godly and learned men, greately ſeene in the Scriptures, who yet are ſoe daily excerciſed in the finding of the meaning of thoſe other places of Scripture, which teach other points neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they finde litle leiſure to looke on ſuch as declare things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Antichriſt, or his ouerthrow. I may not ſay that it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they care litle to vnderſtand the truth of God in theeſe points: for I muſt leaue that to God, who knowes the ſecrets of all hearts. Neuertheleſſe if any of them, who haue a good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, be ſoe careles herein; they may know that it is a fault, ſeeing the holy Ghoſt ſaith concerning the <hi>Reuelation</hi> wherein theeſe things are declared; <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Renel.</hi> 1.3.</note> and they that heare the words of this propheſie, &amp; keepe thoſe things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten therein: for the time is at hand.</hi> And againe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.10.</note> 
               <hi>Seale not the ſayings of the propheſie of this booke; for the time is at hand.</hi> viz. when theeſe things ſhould be fulfilled. Whereby God warneth all men to looke narrowly into this booke, that they may thereby know the <hi>Dragon, Beaſt</hi> and <hi>whore,</hi> and ſuch euils as accompany them, that ſoe they may the better auoide them, and not pertake of theire
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20781:4"/>ſinnes, leſt they receiue of theire plauges; and that eſpetially when theire deliuerance and her ruin are at hand.</p>
            <p>And as this care was neceſſarie in thoſe ages when the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Dragon</hi> reigned, and the firſt <hi>trumpets</hi> ſounded; ſo more eſpetially in theeſe times of the beaſt &amp; whore: wherein the euill they doe is a greate deale worſe, &amp; more dangerous to the Soules of men: for as much as notwithſtanding the light of the Goſpell, <hi>all the world</hi> would ſtill <hi>wonder after him,</hi> for that holines, power and munificence, which they would imagine to reſide in him: and euen many of Gods people would be ſo loth to flee out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that they ſhould be in danger of pertaking of her ſinnes, and receiuing of her plauges; and ſhould haue neede to be daily called on to make them <hi>come out</hi> from her. A duty which as it was euer neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be put in practiſe for the drawing of Soules from her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching delicacies and deceites, ſo more eſpetially now when her greate abhominations are by the refulgent light of Gods Word manifeſted, and her laſt and greateſt plauges muſt needes be approching. For if when <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> wrote, it might be ſaide, <hi>the time is at hand;</hi> how much more in theeſe our times, <hi>vpon whome the ends of the World are come?</hi> and who may ſee, if wee ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſee, or thinke it any ſuch bleſſed thinge to ſee, that the moſt of thoſe things which concerne Antichriſt, and the verrie declining of his Kingdom, are already fulfilled; and thereby eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man warned to waite with a ſtedfaſt faith to ſee the reſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; and not to put farre away (as his fauourers doe) thoſe euill dayes, which ſhall befall him and his friends; and as they doe, who would faine make the World beleeue that he ſhall not be deſtroyed till the ende of the World; and are ſo loth to ſee any thinge proued to the contrary, that they doubt not to affirme that the time can not be ſo much as neerely gueſſed at.</p>
            <p>To whome it may be anſwered that the Lord would neither haue ſaide of the <hi>beaſt,
<note place="margin">Aeuel. 13.</note> He ſhall haue power to doe fourtie and two monethes;</hi> and neither more nor leſſe; nor of the Kings his hornes, <hi>They haue receiued noe Kingdom as yet:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.19.</note> but receiue power as Kings one howre with the Beaſt;</hi> but that he meant to ſhew vs ſome certaine time, which when his ruin ſhould approach, might either be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, or at leaſt verrie neerely found; as in <hi>Daniels</hi> propheticall weekes, wherein euery day ſtands for a yeare: and ſo queſtionleſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20781:4"/>in theeſe <hi>monethes,</hi> which are alſo propheticall monethes, &amp; which can not be literally vnderſtood of three yeares and a halfe. For it followes from the Angels expoſition, that Antichriſt is the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth and eighth head of the ſeauen hilled citie, that is, a head of gouernment in a ſucceſſion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.</note> as the Emperours were of whome he ſaide, one is: <hi>Fiue are fallen, one is, and the other is not yet come.</hi> Fiue of the Roman heads or formes of gouernment were fallen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as <hi>Kings, Conſuls, Dictatours, Decemuiri, &amp; Tribuni Militum.</hi> The ſixt was in the time of Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi> which was the gouernment of the Emperours haueing theire ſeate in <hi>Rome.</hi> This head, ſo longe as it ſhould abide there, would let the comming of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, who was to be the ſeauenth head of the ſame citie,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Reu.</hi> 17.9.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> compared with Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſheweth, ſaying, <hi>only he who now letteth will let, till he be taken out of the way;</hi> he ſaith not till he be vtterly fallen or deſtroied, but taken <hi>out of the way,</hi> viz. remoued; which came to paſſe when the ſeate of the, Empire was remoued from <hi>Rome to Conſtantinople,</hi> and not before: for till then another domineering head could not riſe to rule in <hi>Rome.</hi> Therefore ſaint <hi>John</hi> ſaith of the ſeauenth, <hi>He is not yet come, and when he commeth he muſt continue a ſhort ſpace, And the Beaſt that was and is not, euen he is the eighth, and is of the ſeaven.</hi> This ſeauenth head, which is the Roman gouernment by Biſhops, is ſaide to endure but for a ſhort ſpace, becauſe of the wound, which it ſhould ſoone receiue by the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals;</hi> which when it ſhould be healed was not longe to endure as a ſeauenth head only; but ſhould alſo by reaſon of a new title and authority become an eighth head and more abſolute, that ſoe he might rule and raigne the reſt of his longe time, and doe all the greateſt things aſcribed to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>This eighth head did accordingly beginne in <hi>Boniface III.</hi> when he obtained to be called vniuerſall Biſhop; he then was the eighth, and yet <hi>of the ſeauen,</hi> viz. the ſeauenth, becauſe he ſeemed but to ſucceede the former Biſhops in that gouernment, which they had after the ſeate of the Empire was remoued from <hi>Rome,</hi> and which they got by abuſing the Canons of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Sardica,</hi> as wee ſhall ſee by and by. Howſoeuer ſeeing Antichriſt (ye ſee) is a head of gouernment in a ſucceſſion (as the <hi>Kings,</hi> and after them the other <hi>heads</hi> were, that had liued and ruled in <hi>Rome</hi>)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20781:5"/>theeſe 42. <hi>monethes</hi> giuen to him, can not poſſibly be vnderſtood literally. For indeede it is impoſſible that this ſeauenth head ſhould riſe, be ſeated, wounded, healed, &amp; then become an eighth head, who ſhould firſt be admired and worſhipped by all nations, and then make warre by himſelfe and by his <hi>hornes,</hi> ouercome the <hi>Saints,</hi> yea the <hi>two witneſses,</hi> cauſe an <hi>Image</hi> to be made and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and a <hi>marke</hi> to be taken by <hi>all, ſmall and greate;</hi> yea doe many other greate things mencioned in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> and after ſend to gather the <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth to <hi>Battaile,</hi> and be taken; and all this in three yeares and a halfe. Therefore out of all doubt in theeſe monethes as in <hi>Daniels</hi> weekes <hi>euery day</hi> ſtands for a yeare; as the Lord ſaide to the Iſraelites,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 14.34</note> 
               <hi>After the number of the dayes in which ye ſearched the land, euen forty dayes (each day for a yeare) ſhall ye beare youre iniquities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 4.6.</note> euen <hi>fourtie yeares:</hi> alſo in <hi>Ezechiel, Thou ſhalt beare the iniquitie of the howſe of Iudah fourtie dayes, I haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thee each day for a yeare.</hi> Soe it muſt needes be in theeſe monethes, and ſoe they ſignifie 1260. yeares, as ſome haue iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly collected from Reu. 12.6.14. further alſo that theeſe yeares muſt needes beginne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt the Pope had power to doe, as a head: which ſome thinke beganne in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the greate, when he left <hi>Rome,</hi> when (ſay they) <hi>he that hindred was taken out of the way.</hi> Some ſay ſooner, euen from the time that <hi>Constantine</hi> came to the Empire and the Ethnick gouernment was ouerthrowen or taken out of the way. Indeede it is verry neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that the time ſhould be ſearched out when theeſe 42. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes began; becauſe that is the ſureſt way to finde out the time of his ende and Finall ruin: but the time could not well begin from the time of <hi>Constantine,</hi> or when the Ethnick gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ouerthrowen, or taken out of the way. For by either of theeſe computations, the time ſhould haue beene out many yeares agoe, when indeede diuers Kingdoms were fallen from the Pope and he had noe <hi>power to doe</hi> in them, as in <hi>England, Denmarke</hi> and others, and ſoe indeede as his power began in ſom Kingdoms, before in others, ſoe accordingly God would that he ſhould begin to looſe it in ſome before in others. But yet he hath had, and ſtill hath much power elſwhere to doe great things. Which hath made ſome thinke that the time he hath had ſince, and ſhall yet haue is giuen him for the time of the wound, when (ſay they) <hi>he had noe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20781:5"/>power to doe.</hi> But queſtionleſſe they are miſtaken herein, as the ſequell of this worke will manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And indeede they ſeeme to me to beginne the time to ſoone, I meane not ſoe much before he was a Beaſt, as before he had power <hi>to doe.</hi> For the words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are, <hi>power was giuen him to doe fourtie and two monethes.</hi> Soe <hi>Beza, Aretius, Piſeator,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Pareus</hi> and others reade them, <hi>potestas agendi.</hi> And I can not finde that either he did much, or had much power to doe before the time of <hi>Damaſus</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who was choſen Pope aboute the yeare 366. others ſay 369. and ſate till after the yeare 380. then indeede he had ſome power to doe, (as wee ſhall ſee by &amp; by:) or at the furtheſt in the time of <hi>Syricius,</hi> neere the yeare 386. or thereabouts: to which time of <hi>Damaſus</hi> in the yeare 380. if you adde 1260. yeares, which ſeemes to be the time giuen him in the 42. monethes, they may ende before or aboute the yeare 1640. or at leaſt within a few yeares after, that is, if he had not this time of <hi>doeing</hi> till the dayes of <hi>Syricius,</hi> or <hi>Innocent.</hi> But it may be a litle ſooner, becauſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> might haue power to doe ſome yeares before the yeare 380. And howſoeuer <hi>Rome</hi> may ende much ſooner then the Beaſt: becauſe her deſtruction ſeemeth to many to be by the fifth <hi>viall</hi> Reu. 16. his by ſixth or ſeauenth; hers is firſt declared chap. 18. then his chap. 19. But while wee ſeeme to caſt vp the time ſet foorth in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> this is to be vnderſtood to fall out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts. Firſt if the time of the Beaſts doeing began in the time of <hi>Damaſus</hi> or <hi>Syricius;</hi> and not before or after, which now wee will examin, as needefull to be knowne in theeſe lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table times, wherein the beaſt rageth and preuaileth as if he were to raigne for euer; when indeede it is, becauſe the Deuil in him hath but <hi>a ſhort time.</hi> And ſecondly if <hi>Baronius</hi> and others that I haue followed reckon the yeares right, as for ought that I can perceiue they doe; at leaſt they goe neere the marke; and ſoe therefore may wee.</p>
            <p>As touching the firſt our Lord himſelfe giueth vs light in two places of the <hi>Reuelation.</hi> For while he ſaith of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> Reu. 13. <hi>power was giuen him to doe fourtie and two monethes,</hi> he ſheweth that there is a certaine time when they ſhould beginne, which time may now at the laſt be neerely pointed at, by any that will take the paines to ſearch the Hiſtories, &amp; to ſee whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he firſt had power to doe. The ſecond which is more plaine, and doth indeede ſeeme
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20781:6"/>to ſhew when theeſe monethes were begunne is ſet downe, Reu. 17.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.12.</note> Where it is ſaide of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who are <hi>hornes of the Beaſt; theeſe haue receiued noe Kingdom as yet; but receiue power as Kings one howre with the Beast:</hi> which at the ſooneſt they did not before the time of <hi>Damaſus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ammian. Marcel. lib.</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>lib.</hi> 30. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 29. <hi>c.</hi> 10.11.12.13. <hi>lib.</hi> 31. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> when indeede (as <hi>Ammianus Marcelinus</hi> ſheweth) <hi>the Almanes</hi> had theire King <hi>Marcrianus</hi> of greate puiſſance; the <hi>Burgundians</hi> theires; the <hi>Africans</hi> theires, <hi>Nubel</hi> and then <hi>Firmus;</hi> the <hi>Franckes</hi> theire Kinge <hi>Melobaudes;</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions likewiſe had theires; <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour of the Eaſt was ſlaine by the <hi>Gothes,</hi> who alſo had theire Prince. Or perhaps not ſo ſoone, may ſome man ſay, becauſe after that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> brought them againe into ſome ſubiection to the Roman Empire, which yet rather hindred then ouerthrew theire growing, if not erected Kingdoms; and indeede becauſe he was an Emperour of greate puiſſance, and both greately feared and loued: therefore it may perhaps be thought by ſome that theeſe Kingdoms were not yet erected till after the death of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spaniſh Hiſt. French Hiſt.</note> who gouerned in the dayes of the Emperour <hi>Honorius;</hi> In whoſe time at the fartheſt, as all the beſt Hiſtorians ſhew, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes were plainely erected in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Afrike</hi> by the <hi>Gothes,
<note place="margin">Speede &amp; How. Chron.</note> Vandales, Sueuians &amp; Alanes;</hi> one in <hi>France</hi> vnder <hi>Pharamond;</hi> who yet is ſaide to ſucceede <hi>Marcomir, Sumo</hi> and <hi>Melobaudes.</hi> In whoſe time alſo the <hi>Picts, Scots</hi> and others preuailed in <hi>Britaine;</hi> ſo that after the <hi>Britaines</hi> had elected diuers other Gouernours, they were faine at laſt to chooſe <hi>Vortiger</hi> theire Kinge; and to call in the <hi>Saxons,</hi> who chaſed the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> but ſucceeded them in power and crueltie. Other Barbarous Nations of thoſe times preuailed in <hi>Thracia, Hungarie, Austria, Sclauonia, Panonia, Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia,</hi> and other countries. Thus though the Beaſt might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps haue ſome litle power, to doe a litle, before the riſing of theeſe Kings, yet they who had noe Kingdom before, while the Empire flooriſhed, doe now receiue <hi>power as Kinge one howre with the Beast;</hi> that is to ſay, whether he beganne to haue that more Kingly power <hi>to doe</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> or ſoone after in the time of <hi>Siricius</hi> or <hi>Innocent,</hi> which truly is ſomwhat hard to determin: yet it ſeemes to me to be in the time of <hi>Damaſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reader may alſo giue a good gueſſe thereat, when he ſhall ſee how power was firſt giuen to theeſe Popes, &amp; more then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20781:6"/>to any other Patriarch, or as a Kinde of head ouer all. Which power yet was not giuen him by any plaine and lawfull act of a councell, as both the ſixth <hi>councell of Carthage</hi> aboute the yeare 420. and the councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> aboute the yeare 450. proued againſt him: neither indeede did he get it of many yeares after, nor by conſequence iuſtly; therefore the thinge is not to finde when he had it giuen him lawfully, for that the Antichriſt could not haue; but when ſome things fell out which gaue it him, as it were accidentally; when firſt he tooke hold of ſuch occaſion, and thenceforth openly vſed and maintained it. Which at the ſooneſt, for ought I can finde, was not before the time of <hi>Damaſus:</hi> but he indeede ſtroue to attaine it; and to that ende laide hold of euery litle occaſion, and made vſe of it. For haueing damned the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> in a Councell held ad <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> aboute the yeare 379. he writeth an Epiſtle to the Biſhops of the Eaſt, wherein he intimates vnto them the condemnatory ſentence pronounced againſt <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> and his Diſciple <hi>Timotheus:</hi> which Epiſtle is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited with the ſwelling pride of a loftic minde, breathing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty and preheminence aboue all other Churches, as if the Roman Church were that only Apoſtolike chaire, whereunto all other Churches ought homage and reuerence.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil. Epiſt.</hi> 20. <hi>ad Euſeb. Samoſat.</hi>
               </note> Soe that <hi>S. Baſil</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea</hi> complaines of the pride of the Weſt, becauſe they cared only for theire owne preheminence, but not for the ſtate of theire perſecuted Brethren in the Eaſt vnder the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperour <hi>Valens.</hi> Yea he ſaith that he purpoſed oft times to haue written to the cheife of them, that is to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> that he ſhould not count the
<note n="*" place="margin">Splendor ſuperbiae.</note> 
               <hi>ſplendour of pride</hi> true dignity and honour. Aboute the yeare 380. a generall Councell was aſſembled at <hi>Constantinople.</hi> Whence the Fathers of the Councell wrote vnto <hi>Damaſus,</hi> as to a Brother, and ranke him with other Biſhops of the Weſt, then aſſembled in <hi>Rome,</hi> as theire Letters ſhew,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> vvhich are recited by <hi>Theodoret; To our Brothers and Colleagues, Damaſus, Ambroſe, Britto, Valerian, and other holy Biſhops aſſembled in the greate City of Rome, &amp;c.</hi> He then vvith other Biſhops of the Weſt in a <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> beeing deſired as Brethren to approue the Councell of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> did it: and <hi>Baronius</hi> vvould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs, that he confirmed it as a Superiour, and made it of force. And indeede though <hi>Damaſus</hi> durſt not openly profeſſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20781:7"/>ſo much, yet it ſeemes he was willing to take theire Letters in that ſenſe, and that it ſhould after be thought ſo: for he reſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them as <hi>Sonnes,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>that indeede they had yelded all due reuerence to the See Apoſtolike;</hi> as if he ſaide deſiring to haue youre acts ordered, or confirmed and made good by it. Which howſoeuer it was neuer ſo intented by the Councell, yet it gaue the Popes power to doe as they were diſpoſed then, and euer after to take it, and make vſe of it. For therevpon <hi>Innocent</hi> alſo vſed the ſame ſleight, when the <hi>Mileuitan</hi> Councell Anno 402. and another of <hi>Carthage</hi> Anno 413. had
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Pleſſes Myſt. Iniqui. Progr.</hi> 9.</note> without conſulting with him ordered matters, and then in like manner acquainted him with theire acts, and deſired that he would adde his authority; he anſvvers that they had <hi>had due regard of the Apoſtolicke honour, I ſay of him which had the care and charge of all other Churches.</hi> thus he aſſumed a power ouer Councels, &amp; ſo power to doe as a head.</p>
            <p>But ſome man will ſay, it ſeemes that as yet he had not this power, becauſe the Popes of theſe times were oppoſed, and the power ouer Councels was not yet conferred on him. I anſvver, Antichriſt was to be oppoſed by ſome in all ages, and ſo hath the Pope beene by perticular men, and in many Councels, and euen of late in the Councels of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil;</hi> which declared that a Councell was aboue the Pope: yet he tooke it before, and had it as the Beaſt vvas to haue it, by his ovvne ambitious vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the flatterie of his follovvers. But as far as I can finde not before the time of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> aboute the yeare 380. And then indeede he had alſo begunne to take it vpon him in the caſe of appeales, eſpetially in that Epiſtle vvhich he vvrote to <hi>Stephanus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mauritania,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Council.</note> vvherein he pretendeth that all the greater ſort of cauſes ought to be referred to his hearing, and that they could not be deſcided but by his authority; as alſo that the <hi>prouiſion of Biſhops</hi> belonged to him; vvherein alſo he qualifieth the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> vvith the title of the <hi>Pirmament of all Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>top of all other Churches;</hi> emboldened noe doubt therevnto by Letters ſent before that time vnto him from the ſaide <hi>Stephanies,</hi> vvho complained that certaine Biſhops had beene depoſed in in <hi>Afrike;</hi> adding that this vvas donne, though they all knew well enough, <hi>That Cenſures of Biſhops &amp; all other cauſes of moment ought to be reſerued to the audience of the Biſhop of Rome,</hi> whom he termeth <hi>the Father of Fathers;</hi> and thereby giueth him <hi>power to doe;</hi> himſelfe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20781:7"/>beeing of that broode of Schiſmatiks of whome <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in his dayes, that beeing <hi>cenſured</hi> would preſently croſſe the Seas to <hi>Rome.</hi> And indeede it is the more likely that there had beene ſuch pride or vſurpation in <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and flaterie in his followers: I. Becauſe the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> did not only limit euery <hi>Patriarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> and gaue equall priuileidges to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> but euen declared, that <hi>there was an auncient law and deciſion of the Nicene Councell, that the Biſhops of euery Prouince, with thoſe which dwelt neere vnto them, ſhould ordaine theire owne Ministers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Conſt. Can.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. <hi>Can. Graec.</hi> 3.</note> diuiding the prouinces for the auoidance of confuſion: And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining <hi>that if in any prouince a matter of difference hapened to ariſe, it ſhould be decided by the Synod of the ſame prouince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Becauſe <hi>Syricius</hi> aboute the yeare 386. emboldened as it ſeemes by the power which <hi>Damaſus</hi> had taken, &amp; the flateries of ſuch as followed him, feared not to ſay to <hi>Himerius B. of Aragon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Siricius Epi.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Himer.</hi>
                  </note> That it is not lawfull for any Preiſt of the Lord to be ignorant of the decrees and ſtatutes of the Sea Apoſtolike,</hi> and therefore <hi>requesteth him to make knowne ſuch ordinances &amp; decrees as he ſhould ſend vnto him, not only to thoſe of his owne Dioceſſe, but alſo to thoſe of Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena, Andaluſia, Portugall, Galeace and others,</hi> that is in effect to all the Prouinces of <hi>Spaine; which could not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but be glorious vnto him, who was a Preiſt of ſo longe continuance.</hi> Purpoſing to vſe the ambitious humour of this Prelate to extend his authority, law and traditions through <hi>Spaine.</hi> And in his 4. Epiſtle to the Biſhops of <hi>Afrike, That without the priuitie of the Sea Apostolike, that is to ſay of the Primate, none might preſume to ordaine a Biſhop.</hi> All which makes it moſt cleare that he had the <hi>power to doe,</hi> which the Beaſt was to haue in the beginning of his raigne. His ambition was ſo appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and men in thoſe times ſo prone to flatter him with titles, that in remedy thereof, the third Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> anno 397. (<hi>Siricius</hi> then ſitting Pope) decreed, <hi>That the Biſhop of the firſt See ſhould not be called the Prince or Cheife of Prieſts, or high Prieſt, or by any other ſuch name, but only the Biſhop of the firſt See.</hi> As for the name of vniuerſall Biſhop, <hi>that the Biſhop of Rome it ſelfe ſhould not be called by that name.</hi> Which ſhewes that theeſe titles had beene giuen him by ſome flatterers in thoſe dayes, or why elſe ſhould the Councell make this Canon? this <hi>Siricius,</hi> to ſhew the Beaſt was riſen &amp; had power to doe, ſtabliſhed the forbiddance of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20781:8"/>Preiſts marriages, though by generall conſent it had beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected in the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and was not receiued in the Weſt of 600. yeares after, doe his Succeſſors what they could.</p>
            <p>After him came <hi>Innocent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Innocent. Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Victric.</hi>
               </note> anno 401. He, in his 2. Epiſtle to <hi>Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricius</hi> B. of <hi>Roan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> publiſhed this generall decree, <hi>That the greater cauſes after that they had beene cenſured by the Biſhop ſhould be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the See of Rome, as the Synod</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath ordained, and the laudable vſe and custome of the Church requireth.</hi> He and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors <hi>Zozimus, Boniface,</hi> and <hi>Celeſtine</hi> would haue men thinke that the councell of <hi>Nice</hi> had ſoe ordained: which that councell did not, as the 6. councell of <hi>Carthago</hi> proued againſt them aboute the yeare 420. and ſoe did the generall councels of <hi>Constantinople</hi> and <hi>Chacedon.</hi> It was indeede the councell of <hi>Sardica,</hi> aboute the yeare 350. that gaue this power to <hi>Iulius;</hi> but that canon neuer put in practiſe by him, was reuoked in expreſſe termes in the councell of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople, can. 3. which councell had now beene approued by <hi>Damaſus:</hi> therefore they would not name it to be a canon of <hi>Sardica,</hi> but pretend it to be a canon of <hi>Nice.</hi> Which forgerie many perceiued not, and therefore gaue him power to doe. But if any man will yet obiect and ſay, It ſeemes he had not yet this power, becauſe the councels of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the 6. councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and the councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> oppoſed it. I anſwer here as before, Antechriſt was to be oppoſed by ſome in all ages, and ſo hath the Pope, and euen of late in the Councels of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſile,</hi> but yet he had power, as the Beaſt was to haue it, by his owne arogant vſurpation &amp; the flaterie of his followers, and that I thinke aboute the yeare 380. in the time of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> or ſoone after, and not before: and ſo as I ſaide his time may expire aboute the yeare 1640. or within few yeares after, that is if his terme of doeing began not till the time of <hi>Siricius.</hi> Others perhaps will ſay he had it much ſooner. Here I muſt tell the Papiſts, that it is to noe purpoſe for them to bringe for a ground of appeales, or the antiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> of them, the acts of any perticular Heretike, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matike or Superſtitious Doter before the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>myſterie</hi> did <hi>worke</hi> in the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es time, and if it were graunted that <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> and <hi>Valentinia</hi> Hereticks had recourſe to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had, who were depoſed for ſacrificing to idols, and likewiſe diuers Sciſmatiks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20781:8"/>of <hi>Afrike</hi> in the time of <hi>Cyprian:</hi> yet this proues not that they might appeale, or he receiue: for if the Pope had <hi>had</hi> any ſuch right, then would not <hi>Cyprian</hi> haue complained of them for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing, nor of him for receiuing; neither would the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> haue limited his power, and giuen as much to <hi>Alexandria.</hi> But howſoeuer, the queſtion is here of power that was giuen to the Beaſt after his riſing; which could not be before the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, becauſe he that hindred was not then <hi>taken out of the way,</hi> the Emperour not fully departed to <hi>Constantin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither could the <hi>burning mountaine</hi> (ſignified vnder the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond trumpet,</hi> Reu. 8.8.) be caſt <hi>into the ſea</hi> before the Nicene Councell; which will appeare to be the ſea, as they abuſed it to riſe out of it. But indeede <hi>this burning mountaine</hi> was either caſt into the ſea in the time of the Councell, when the Pope by his deputies might ambitiouſly craue of the Emperour, or of the Councell, that his might be the firſt ſee, and haue ſome preeminence in power; or elſe (as I rather thinke) ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne after before the fall of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> into <hi>Arianiſme</hi> (ſignified vnder the third trumpet, Reu. 8.10.) when the Pope alleaged the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell for his authority, as <hi>Iulius</hi> did: and thenceforth the beaſt might indeede begin to riſe and <hi>doe:</hi> yet I thinke he had not this <hi>power to doe</hi> before the time of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> nor longe before the yeare 380. or perhaps not till the time of <hi>Syricius,</hi> aboute the yeare 386. or ſoone after. For though wee finde in <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Soſomene,</hi> that before that <hi>Iulius</hi> tooke vpon him by abſolute authority
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Edit. lat. Sozom. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>to reſtore ſundrie Biſhops of the Eaſterne</hi> Churches depoſed for diuers cauſes by theire <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, becauſe</hi> ſaith he <hi>the care of all Churches belonged to him by reaſon of his ſee, therefore he wrote to the Biſhops of the Eaſt telling them that they had donne verrie ill to determin and conclude any thinge againſt thoſe Biſhops without his priuitie;</hi> yet as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Soſom</hi> ſhew, <hi>they tooke his reproofes in ſcorne, and calling a Synod at Antioch, by common aduiſe &amp; conſent retourne his imputations backe vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with all bitterneſſe, telling him that he was no more to controll the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they thought fit to depriue any man in theire Churches, than they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedled at what time Nouatus was cast out of the Church of Rome:</hi> Soſomene addeth, <hi>That theire anſwer was full of ſcoffes and threats, &amp;c.</hi> Thus as yet they gaue him noe power to doe. And it ſeemeth that this anſwer wrought vpon him: for in his next letter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20781:9"/>he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plained only that they called him not to theire <hi>Synod;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before he pretended, that they might not call a Councell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his authority: he doth not alleadge for himſelfe that either by virtue of his ſucceſſion to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> or of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, they ought to appeale to <hi>Rome;</hi> his words are only theeſe, <hi>The Fathers of Nice ordained, and that not without the counſell of God, that the acts of one Councell ſhould be examined in another:</hi> whereby appeares noe greater power giuen to the B. of <hi>Rome</hi> ouer <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> than to the B. of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ouer <hi>Rome.</hi> As for the greiuance whereof he complaineth, it is only this, that <hi>contrary to the cuſtome, they had not written firſt of all vnto him,</hi> concerning the differences amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue his aduice for compoſing of them, as beeing Biſhop of the firſt ſee; as alſo that many <hi>Synods</hi> had beene held in the Eaſt, concerning points of faith and doctrine, without giueing him notice thereof, <hi>contrary to the Rule and canon of the Church; wherein is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, that none might impoſe any law vpon the Churches without the aduice of the Biſhop of Rome.</hi> This canon gaue him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede that he ſhould either be called and haue a voice in euery Councell that impoſed lawes, or at leaſt that his aduiſe &amp; conſent ſhould be aſked if he ſhould be farre away, as fell out at the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where <hi>Damaſus</hi> was neither in Perſon nor by his deputies; and in noe other ſenſe did <hi>Iulius</hi> now alleadge it: he complaineth not that they aſſembled without his leaue, but that they neither called him, nor vſed his aduiſe; he doth not ſay that this giues him that he ſhould be as a head or Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, to confirme or abrogate at his pleaſure; much leſſe that he ſhould impoſe what law he liſt. He knew well enough that it made him noe more then a <hi>Patriarch,</hi> that other <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> were his brethren, and that euery Biſhop had neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe a free voice as well as he. Neither did he now expound it, that this canon gaue him this priueleidge as to a Superiour, to whome ſuch homage was due: therefore <hi>Iulius</hi> bad not this power to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Damaſus</hi> as I ſhewed ſeemeth to haue beene the firſt that tooke it in that proud ſenſe; and yet not verrie plainely, but ſomwhat tacitely in words of doubtfull ſignification, as ye ſaw. After him <hi>Siricius</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> were more plaine, as I ſhewed. And ſoe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede he roſe out of that <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> by forging one canon, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20781:9"/>wreſting another: a weake foundation for ſo mightie a building; yet ſuch and noe other was the foundation of this Kingdom. And thus indeede one Canon of <hi>Nice</hi> gaue him power to doe: yet not as the Councell meant it, but as he in time tooke it. And ſo he had it, but not before the time of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> or <hi>Syricius.</hi> For <hi>Iulius</hi> as ye ſee had not ſo much power giuen him: and <hi>Liberius</hi> his next Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, muſt needes haue leſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baron. Vol.</hi> 4. <hi>Anno</hi> 365. <hi>art.</hi> 1.2.3.4.5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſeeing he was conuicted of Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, as after all excuſes <hi>Baronius</hi> is forced to confeſſe, beholding many proofes thereof. <hi>And if</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there were noe other proofe, his owne Letters are ſufficient to put it out of question.</hi> And indeede he wrote to the Biſhops of the Eaſt on this manner,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. Liberij ad Oriental, apud Hilar. in Fragment.</note> 
               <hi>I cast of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius from our communion, not daining ſo much as to receiue his Letters: I maintaine peace with you, embracing the confeſſion of the Sirmian Councell.</hi> Which was all one as if he had in expreſſe words renounced the Councell of <hi>Nice:</hi> and therefore, He could haue noe power by it; nor indeede by that of <hi>Sardica,</hi> which had giuen more to <hi>Iulius,</hi> becauſe that had confirmed the <hi>Nicene</hi> faith, to which this of <hi>Sirmium</hi> was oppoſit. Yet heere by the way wee may ſee what greate inconuenience would follow, if either of thoſe Councels of <hi>Nice</hi> or <hi>Sardica</hi> muſt needes be in that point of force vnto all ages: for while <hi>Liberius</hi> ratifieth the ſentence againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and confirmeth the Councell of <hi>Sirmium,</hi> if the Councels of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Sardica</hi> giue the Pope this abſolute power of confirming or abrogating Councels, then they make this act of <hi>Liberius</hi> lawfull, and thereby vtterly ouerthrow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and theire owne faith and confeſſion, which was contrarie: but the Papiſts will confeſſe that the Councels of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica</hi> doe not make this act of <hi>Liberius</hi> lawfull; vvhich to confeſſe is as much as if they acknowledged that thoſe Councels did not giue abſolute power to the Pope, to confirme or abrogate the Decrees of Councels.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer ye ſee <hi>Liberius</hi> could not well haue this power to doe. But then after him came <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and he indeede was a man of more reſpect, learned, and of ſuch good parts, as couered his ambition, ſo that ſome could not ſee it, and others were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps content to winke at it; he therefore after a while might the better chalenge ſome Priueleidge from that Canon of <hi>Nice.</hi> And noe doubt but that the words of <hi>Hoſius</hi> vttered not longe before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20781:10"/>his time in the Councell of <hi>Sardica,</hi> vvhereof they ſo much boaſt, did now further him in his deſired power. The words of the Canon are theeſe: <hi>Hoſius the Biſhop ſaide, if any Biſhop be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in any cauſe, if the partie condemned thinke he haue iuſt cauſe not to ſtand to the ſentence, if it pleaſe you, let vs yeeld this honour to S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Let the matter be ſignified by Letter to</hi> Iulius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>to the ende that he, with other Biſhops of the Dioces, may enter againe into the knowledge of the cauſe.</hi> Now obſerue here: 1. That it was <hi>Hoſius</hi> that propoſed it; and he propoſed it as a new antidote againſt a poyſen, conſidering that the Biſhops of the Eaſt were for the greater part at that time infected with <hi>Arianiſme,</hi> reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it to the perſon of <hi>Iulius,</hi> and would noe doubt haue donne otherwiſe in the perſon of <hi>Liberius,</hi> Succeſſor vnto <hi>Iulius,</hi> and a profeſſed <hi>Arrian,</hi> notvvithſtanding the pretended Chaire of <hi>Saint Peter.</hi> 2. Note theeſe words, <hi>If it pleaſe you, let vs honour the memorie of S. Peter:</hi> for had this beene an auncient right, ſhould he not rather haue ſaide, Let vs obſerue the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord, or the auncient order of the Church, or the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of <hi>Nice,</hi> vvhereby it is ordained that men might appeale to <hi>Rome.</hi> 3. Is it reaſon that a Canon of a Nationall Councell ſhould conclude and binde the Church in generall? 4. This Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſo made, and neuer practiſed was in expreſſe termes reuoked in the generall Councell of <hi>Constantinople</hi> Can. 3. and in that of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> Can. 8. This was the firſt that ſeemed to giue him any greate power; but this as ye ſee vvas not abſolute, yet hence he tooke ſuch occaſion of riſing, that ſome haue thought that he did riſe out of it. But that vvee may finde the truth hereof, obſerue: Doctrines are in holy Scriptures called <hi>waters:</hi> vvhereof ſome vvaters are cleane Ezech. 47.1. Ioel 3.18. Zach. 14.8. Reu. 15.2. ſome corrupted Reu. 8.10.11. chap. 16.3.4. ſome not corrupt of themſelues, but partly made ſo by reaſon of ſomwhat caſt into them: ſo was it vvith that Sea into vvhich the <hi>burning mountaine</hi> was caſt, Reuel. 8.8. <hi>and the third part of the Sea became blood,</hi> and out of that Sea the <hi>Beaſt aroſe.</hi> Reuel. 13. Now that vvce may know vvhat that Sea is, obſerue: The Sea is the place vvhere wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are gathered and meete together. <hi>Riuers</hi> and Fountaines runne into the Sea, and emptie themſelues there. Novv Riuers and Fountaines doe ſignifie the Doctors and Teachers, from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20781:10"/>vvhome the doctrines, that is the <hi>waters,</hi> flovv.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 8.10.</note> So vvhen <hi>the third Angell ſounded, a greate ſtarre fell from Heauen, and it fell vpon the third part of the Riuers and Fountaines of waters:</hi> this greate Starre vvas <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperour, vvho fell into the <hi>Arrian</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; and he fell vpon part of the <hi>Riuers and Fountaines,</hi> viz. Biſhops and Teachers, vvho vvere corrupted by him, ſome by perſvvaſion and ſmoth deuices, but moſt by force and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. By vvhich meanes many vvere corrupted, &amp; amonge others Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third viall</hi> is povvred on ſuch corrupt <hi>riuers</hi> &amp; <hi>Fountaines</hi> as are defiled vvith the filth of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 16.4.</note> and come from the mouth of the Beaſt and falſe Prophet. Novv the place vvhere ſuch riuers and Fountaines meere, and empty themſelues muſt needes be a <hi>Sea:</hi> this is in Councels, vvhoſe doctrines and canons are therefore called <hi>the Sea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3.</note> Therefore vvhen <hi>the ſecond Angel poured out his vial on the Sea:</hi> this vvas on an aſſembly or Councell of Antichriſtian doctors, and on theire vvaters or doctrines, vvhich he manifeſteth to be corrupt and perintious; this was on the Councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> which was performed by <hi>Chemnitius. Examen. Concil. Tride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Or at leaſt by him and others, that alſo writ againſt that Councell. But the Sea out of which the Beaſt <hi>aroſe</hi> was not ſo corrupt in it ſelfe, but only became ſoe in ſome part thereof, into which the burning mountaine was caſt, which corrupted it. Now if one ſhould aſke me whether the Sea out of which the Beaſt aroſe were the Councill of <hi>Nice,</hi> or that of <hi>Sardica?</hi> I thinke that if not out of both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and put together by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then rather out of that of <hi>Nice.</hi> I. Becauſe that was a generall Councell, and therefore more apt for his purpoſe and authority, as the other was not, which only reſtrained to the perſon of <hi>Iulius</hi> a priueleidge ſoone after reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. 2. Becauſe that of <hi>Nice</hi> gaue him prioritie of place, and this priueleidge that <hi>a law</hi> ſhould not be impoſed on the Church without his aduiſe: out of which, as he tooke it, he (as ye ſaw) made greate aduantage, and indeede roſe out of it, this beeing the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall and ground of all the power he after got. 3. Becauſe he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies alleadged it for his authority; which it ſeemes he the rather did, becauſe it was generall, and the more auncient &amp; more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced; and indeede becauſe that Canon of <hi>Sardica</hi> was ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked: yea he ſo much deſired to riſe out of the <hi>Nicene Councell,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20781:11"/>that in alleadging as he pretended a Canon of <hi>Nice,</hi> he vſeth the very words of this Canon of <hi>Sardica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Myſterie of Iniquitie, written by M. du Pleſſes.</note> only leaueing out the name <hi>Iulius,</hi> and was therefore conuicted of forgerie by the ſixt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Carthage.</hi> 4. Becauſe the burning mountaine ſignified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſecond trumpet, muſt needes be caſt into the Sea before the fall of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> vpon the riuers, ſignified vnder the third, and therefore in all likelihood before the Councell of <hi>Sardica;</hi> which yet gaue him power, or increaſed it, as he tooke it. But by reaſon that <hi>Liberius,</hi> who preſently ſucceeded, was an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and therefore could neither chalenge power by it, nor by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, this power, as I ſhewed, was not excerciſed till the time of <hi>Damaſus.</hi> But indeede ye haue ſeene that from the time of <hi>Damaſus</hi> or <hi>Siricius,</hi> the Pope (as he vſed the matter) had power to doe in things that belonged to other mens iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yea as an ouerſeer and confirmer of Councells, as he tooke the matter; and what more as a kinde of head and lawgiuer, as ye ſaw in the Epiſtle of <hi>Siricius</hi> to <hi>Himerius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aragon:</hi> and the Beaſt muſt needes be then riſen, and in action, becauſe ſoone after he began to receiue wounds, and at laſt his deadly wound, by the incurſions of the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus power was giuen him to doe, and thus he had it, but not ſo ſoone as ſome haue thought. So that they who reckon his time of doeing from the time that <hi>Constantine</hi> came to the Empire, or when the heathen Emperour was caſt out, or from the time of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, or from the time that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> left <hi>Rome,</hi> or from the time of Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> may beginne to ſoone. And if not, then it muſt needes be vnderſtood as others haue obſerued, <hi>power was giuen him to doe fourtie and two monethes;</hi> but in the time of the wound by the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> or at leaſt while it was ſore and deadly, he had noe power to doe; therefore thoſe yeares of the vvound, vvherein he could doe nothing, muſt not be reckoned, vnleſſe you allovv others for them: Which yet may be fevver by many than ſome haue thought; becauſe the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> did not raigne ſo longe in <hi>Rome,</hi> as they ſay; and ſo the time of the vvound beeing leſſe then they giue, vvill bringe it to the ſame reckoning vvee make, or very neere it. But indeede there is noe cauſe to expound it ſo, becauſe it is cleare enough that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> vvas not riſen, or at leaſt had not <hi>power to doe</hi> ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20781:11"/>ſoone as they thinke; and withall that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time that the <hi>Gothes</hi> firſt tooke <hi>Rome</hi> to theire expulſion the Pope, had for the moſt part, power enough to doe, which is verrie behoofull to manifeſt; becauſe men may thereby ſee that there is noe allowance to be giuen him for the time of the wound, or if any, yet but litle. For <hi>Rome</hi> was more than once ſaued and reſcued; and though it were taken againe, yet the Popes of thoſe times had as much power to doe, as euer theire predeceſſors had, if not more. Beſides the <hi>Gothes</hi> became Chriſtians; many of them were indeede but Arrians; yet <hi>Baronius</hi> ſheweth that they gaue the Pope much power to doe: and queſtionles theire Kingdom did rather further the myſterie of iniquitie then hinder it, as wee ſhall ſee by and by. Therefore out of doubt they are much miſtaken, who giue 140. yeares for the time of the <hi>Gothes Kingdom,</hi> begining is when <hi>Alaricus</hi> firſt tooke <hi>Rome,</hi> which they ſay was aboute the yeare 415. and ending it when <hi>Narſes</hi> vanquiſhed <hi>Totilas.</hi> Whereas others better ſkilled in hiſtorie ſhew that theire Kingdom laſted but 72. yeares: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining the time after the firſt comming of <hi>Theodoricus</hi> into <hi>Italie,</hi> and ending it as the former, when <hi>Totilas</hi> was vanquiſhed. And yet before that, extirpation of <hi>Totilas, Beliſares</hi> the Emperours Leiftenant had entred <hi>Rome,</hi> taken <hi>Vitiges</hi> Kinge of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and carried him captiue to <hi>Constantinople;</hi> and after that when the <hi>Gothes,</hi> haueing choſen <hi>Totilas</hi> for theire Kinge, tooke <hi>Rome</hi> againe, <hi>Beliſares</hi> recouered it the ſecond time: But in his abſence they got ſtrength, wonne it againe, &amp; then <hi>Narſes</hi> wholly expelled them out of <hi>Italie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſee theire errour who begin theire Kingdom ſo ſoone, and reckon the time of the wound to be 140. yeares. Begining them in that time of <hi>Honorius</hi> wherein <hi>Rome</hi> was firſt taken. For themſelues confeſſe that during the raigne of <hi>Honorius, Rome was twiſe taken, Alaricus and Ataulphus beeing the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and yet the Beaſt had not the deadly wound in the head, ſeeing it was rather a ſhamefull then a harmefull ouerthrow</hi> (as <hi>Pompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Laetus</hi> ſheweth in the life of <hi>Honorius;</hi>) <hi>that when Honorius began to rouſe vp himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sabell. En.</hi> 8. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> the Gothes were expelled out of Italie, and Attalus theire Kinge led in triumph to Rome,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20781:12"/>and after his right hand was cut off, he was carried captiue to</hi> Lipara; <hi>that ſo longe as</hi> Honorius <hi>and</hi> Valentinian <hi>liued, the Maiestie of the Empire was defended by theire Leiftenants</hi> Conſtantius <hi>and</hi> Aëtius, <hi>though theire Maiſters were ſlacke</hi> and laſie. Yet <hi>Valentinian</hi> raigned many yeares after <hi>Honorius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, that before that <hi>Alaricus</hi> had taken <hi>Rome;</hi> but he gaue life to ſuch as fled to Chriſtian Churches; and then led his armie from <hi>Rome</hi> with purpoſe to ſaile into <hi>Afrike,</hi> and ſetle his abode there: but eare longe he died. After his deſeaſe <hi>Ataulphus</hi> his Kinſman returned to <hi>Rome</hi> with the <hi>Gothes,</hi> reſoluing to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all there, to build another citie, to change the name of it, &amp; call it <hi>Gothia:</hi> but his wife <hi>Placidia</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Honorius</hi> with perſwaſions diuerted him: and the <hi>Gothes</hi> then departed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed themſelues toward <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> Soe that it ſeemes the deadly wound was not yet giuen, nor the Popes power of doeing taken ſhort by them. For indeede <hi>Zozimus, Boniface &amp; Celestine</hi> tooke much on them in this time. And the Emperour <hi>Valentinian,</hi> who raigned longe after that in the weſt, couenanted with the <hi>Vandals</hi> &amp; aſſigned them bounds in <hi>Afrike</hi> to dwell in. And ſoe in his time <hi>Sixtus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Celestine</hi> in the papacie, and ruled 8. yeares, free enough from this wound; and after him <hi>Leo</hi> was in quiet enough for a longe time; but in his dayes indeede <hi>Attilas</hi> King of the <hi>Hunnes</hi> inuaded <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſo did <hi>Genſericus</hi> Kinge of the <hi>Vandals</hi> ſhortly after: but <hi>Leo</hi> by his eloquence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed <hi>Rome</hi> from fire, when both <hi>Attilas</hi> and <hi>Genſericus</hi> would haue burned it. The later was neere aboute the yeare 450: and it hath beene thought a terrible blow: but it ſeemed, the deadly wound was not yet giuen till the time of <hi>Odoacer and Theodoricus.</hi> For <hi>Genſericus</hi> departed into <hi>Afrike,</hi> and the Popes after this had but too much power, as wee ſhall ſee by and by. <hi>Odoacer</hi> indeede inuaded it, tooke it, and beſides the greateſt part of <hi>Italie,</hi> ſlew <hi>Oreſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 472.</note> and compelled his Sonne <hi>Augustulus</hi> to denude himſelfe of Imperiall honours; whereby the weſterne Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> was for a time extinct,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baron. Vol.</hi> 6. <hi>an.</hi> 476. <hi>art.</hi> 1.2.3.</note> while that <hi>Odoacer</hi> now raigned there. Yet as <hi>Baronius</hi> and others ſhew, he did not moleſt the Pope &amp; Clergie. <hi>Theodoricus</hi> killed him &amp; raigned alone in <hi>Italie</hi> for many yeares. But eare longe after his death the <hi>Gothes</hi> were beaten out of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Beliſares and Narſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20781:12"/>
            <p>Some perhaps will thinke that the deadly blow vvas not giuen till the time of <hi>Totilas,</hi> after <hi>Beliſares</hi> had recouered Rome; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Totilas</hi> tooke it againe aboute the yeare 547. And this vvas indeede the moſt fearefull deſolation that euer it had; in ſo much that this Kinge vvas called <hi>Flagellum Dei,</hi> that is the ſcourge of God. He caſt dovvne part of the vvalls, burned the hovvſes, killed the <hi>Citizens,</hi> ſo that neither man nor vvoman remained therein for 40. dayes. I anſvver if this vvere the vvound, it laſted not: for he vvas ſoone vanquiſhed by <hi>Narſes.</hi> And if the vvound vvere before in the time of <hi>Odoacer,</hi> or <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> or ſooner; yet the matter is not to ſee hovv longe the vvound laſted vnhealed; but vvhether it hindred the Popes povver of doeing for all that time. Wee haue ſeene already to <hi>Leo;</hi> vvho ruled 21. yeares, &amp; indeede tooke much on him, as appeared to the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon:</hi> but the Papiſts are ready enough to boaſt and ſhevv you vvhat greate povver he had to doe. After him <hi>Hilarius</hi> continued 7. yeares. <hi>Simplicius</hi> ſucceeded &amp; continued 15. yeares. What power theeſe had, may appeare by theire Succeſſour, vvho liued in a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time. This vvas <hi>Foelix</hi> the III. vvho continued neere 9. yeares. He gouerned the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Zeno,</hi> vvhen <hi>Odoacer</hi> and <hi>Theodoricus</hi> contended for the Superioritie of <hi>Italie.</hi> He vvas nothing inferiour to his Anteceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in zeale to aduance the Supremacie of the <hi>Roman</hi> Chaire. For he was ſo bold as to excomunicate <hi>Acatius Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> becauſe when <hi>Petrus Moggus</hi> gaue teſtimonie of his repentance, and the recantation of his errour, <hi>Acatius</hi> abſolued him, and did not craue the aduiſe of <hi>Foelix,</hi> when he receiued him, like as he craued his aduiſe before, when he excomunicated him, though now, there was leſſe neede, while <hi>Moggus</hi> teſtified his repentance and recantation. And herevpon <hi>Gelaſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gelaſ. in Epiſ. ad Dardanos.</note> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Foelix,</hi> grew ſo inſolent as to depriue <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> of the right of Patriarchſhip, and to <hi>pronounce that the See of Rome might without a Synod of himſelfe either abſolue thoſe whome a Synod had wrongfully condemned, or condemne ſuch as had deſerued it;</hi> and ſo ſetteth vp his See aboue all Councells. And againe, <hi>The Canon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> ſaith he, <hi>hath ordained that all Churches ought to appeale to this See, and from this See to none; becauſe this See iudgeth of all Churches, and noe Church of it, as beeing without ſpot or wrinkle.</hi> Yet (as God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20781:13"/>iuſtly permitted) after this vaine boaſting, his next Succeſſor <hi>Anaſtatius had ſecret communion with the Accatian Hereticks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liber pontif.</note> as the Pontificall booke ſheweth, adding, <hi>That therefore many Preiſts, and others of the Clergie withdrew themſelues from his communion, &amp;c. Symachus</hi> ſucceeded, though not by full or plaine election; for many held for <hi>Laurence,</hi> and each Faction kept quarter apart, till ſome beeing wiſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome, the matter was referred to <hi>Theodorik</hi> the King; who preferred <hi>Symachus:</hi> and yet 4. yeares after <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> was called home againe, &amp; the Factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fell fairely to blowes, wherein were infinite ſpoiles <hi>and murders committed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paulus Diaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Nicephor. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 35.</note> as <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> ſhew. After <hi>Symachus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſda,</hi> who would looſe noe time. If we may beleeue his Epiſtles, he made diuers Biſhops his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icars</hi> in ſundrie Prouinces of the Weſt: as <hi>Auitus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vienna</hi> in the Prouince of <hi>Narbona, Iohn</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> in <hi>Spanie</hi> on this ſide the riuer <hi>Betis;</hi> and on the otherſide <hi>Salust</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Seuill.</hi> Theeſe Biſhops deſiring prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie and ſuperioritie accepted of this title, and ſoe gaue the Pope much power to doe in thoſe times, at leaſt by his Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
            <p>And indeede howſoeuer ſome thinke that the <hi>Gothes</hi> Kingdom tooke away, or hindred the Popes power of doeing, as it might ſeeme at ſome times, for a litle while: Yet to ſay truth for the moſt part it furthered and increaſed it. For the Emperours power was now bounded in the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> and yet to recouer authority in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> they thought fit to hold intelligence with the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to make faire wether with them, by theire meanes to finde a doore open into <hi>Italie.</hi> And therefore whereas diuers Emperours had fauoured ſome herecies which the Popes had oppoſed, <hi>Iuſtine</hi> the Emperour, to be more pleaſing to the Pope, was contented to ſend to conſult with him vpon certaine points of faith: which though it were no verrie greate matter, ſeeing diuers Emperours haue donne as much with ſome Preiſts, and <hi>Monkes,</hi> that haue beene famous for learning, iudgement and integritie; as <hi>Charles</hi> the greate with <hi>Bertram</hi> a Preiſt aboute tranſubſtantiation: Yet the Popes ye may be ſure would in time make greate matters of theeſe preſidents. Wherefore <hi>Baronius</hi> maketh much of a certaine ſentence taken out of a letter which <hi>Iuſtine</hi> wrote to <hi>Hormiſda:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baron. vol.</hi> 7 <hi>an.</hi> 519. <hi>art.</hi> 98.</note> which ſentence he cauſeth to be printed in greate letters: <hi>Wee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20781:13"/>beleeue and hold for Catholike, that which was intimated to vs by youre religious anſwer.</hi> Soe dangerous it is to deale fairely with theeſe men. For <hi>Baronius</hi> thinks he hath gotten a greate ground of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie in that the Emperour <hi>Iustine,</hi> and after him <hi>Iustinian</hi> ſent vnto the Popes a confeſſion of theire faith; which though they often did as much to other Biſhops, and might haue donne it to Preiſts alſo, without any giueing of ſupremacie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet as the Popes were pleaſed to take the matter, it gaue them power to doe. After <hi>Hormiſda</hi> came <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. <hi>Theodoric</hi> the Kinge ſent him Ambaſſodor to <hi>Iustine,</hi> to craue that the <hi>Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Biſhops whome he had bainſhed might be reſtored to theire places againe: elſe the Catholike Biſhops in <hi>Italie</hi> ſhould expect the like at his hands:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liber Fontif. in Iohan.</hi> 1.</note> which made Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> with teares to perſwade the Emperour to condeſcend. Here the Emperour, ſtill willing for a further ende, to pleaſe the Pope did him ſome honour: which yet as they take the matter gaue him power. But it ſoe diſpleaſed <hi>Theodoric,</hi> that at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne he clapt him in priſon, where he ended his life.
<note place="margin">Platina.</note> 
               <hi>Foelix</hi> the 4. ſucceeded and ruled 4. yeares. He excomunicated <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople</hi> for hereſie; he ordained that Chriſtians before theire departure out of this life ſhould be anointed with oyle: This is theire Sacrament of extreme vnction, inſtituted as ye ſee by him. Whome <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſecond ſucceeded, though not without ſchiſme: for <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> was competitor while he liued. In his time <hi>Eulalius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſubmitted himſelfe vnto the chaire of <hi>Rome:</hi> whereupon <hi>Boniface</hi> tooke occaſion of inſolent inſulting, and that ſo far, that he is not aſhamed to write of <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> Biſhop of Carthage, <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo,</hi> and of the reſt of the Fathers which were preſent at the ſixt Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> that they <hi>through the inſtigation of the deuill in the time of our Predeceſſours Boniface and Celeſtine began to exalt themſelues againſt the Church of Rome: But Eulalius</hi> ſaith he <hi>now Biſhop of Carthage, ſeeing himſelfe through the ſinne of</hi> Aurelius <hi>to ſtand ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the communion of the Roman Church, hath repented him thereof, intreating to be receiued &amp;c.</hi> This indeede gaue them greate power to doe, as they inſolently tooke it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond ſucceeded, whenas the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> beeing newly come to the crowne, that he might pleaſe the Pope, and get freinds in <hi>Italie,</hi> ſent to him, to aſſure him of his true
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20781:14"/>faith. <hi>Baronius</hi> here obſerueth that, in his Epiſtle, he ſaith in this manner; <hi>Wee are all carefull to aduertiſe youre holineſſe of all ſuch things as concerne the eſtate of the Church; wee indeauour to ſubmit and to vnite vnto youre holineſſe all the Biſhops of the Eaſt.</hi> Which words Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> laide hold on with both his hands in his anſwer to this letter; where he telleth him, that amonge other his vertues, this was moſt eminent, that he <hi>ſubiected all things to the See of Rome:</hi> whereas the Emperour meant only to indeauour that the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of the Eaſt ſhould ſubmit to the faith, and ſoe be vinted to <hi>Iohn</hi> and other Biſhops that profeſſed it. Beſides he, and other Emperours had ſaide as much to the Patriarch of Conſtantinople and other Biſhops,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pleſſes myſt. Iniquit. prog.</hi> 17.</note> as Mounſeire du <hi>Pleſſes</hi> hath proued. Yet thus the Gothes Kingdom rather furthered the Popes power then hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it, while in thoſe times the Emperour, to regaine <hi>Italie,</hi> gaue him fairer words then otherwiſe he would haue donne. <hi>Agapetus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Iohn,</hi> and was preſently ſent, by <hi>Theodatus</hi> the Kinge, to <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> to pacifie him for the ſlaughter of <hi>Amalaſuntha</hi> his wife; a fit commiſſion for a Pope. When he came a Councell was called at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein <hi>Anthimius</hi> the Patriarch thereof, beeing an <hi>Eutichean</hi> Heretick, was depoſed. And the truth is that <hi>Agapete</hi> beeing then at <hi>Constantinople</hi> preſided in the Councell wherein <hi>Anthimius</hi> was depoſed, and <hi>Menas</hi> placed in his roome; which as Popes would take it, gaue them much power: he died there. And then <hi>Siluerius</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Hormiſda,</hi> ſomtime Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſucceeded. He gouerned when <hi>Iustinian</hi> ſent <hi>Beliſares</hi> to fight againſt <hi>Vitiges. Theodora</hi> the Empreſſe ſent to <hi>Siluerius</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to yeeld to the reſtoring of <hi>Anthimius,</hi> and depoſing of <hi>Menas: Siluerius</hi> refuſed: wherefore <hi>Theodora</hi> ſent to <hi>Beliſares</hi> to Baniſh <hi>Siluerius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baron. vol.</hi> 7. <hi>an.</hi> 538. <hi>art.</hi> 20.</note> and to appoint <hi>Vigilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who had promiſed to fulfill her deſires: which was donne accordingly. Wherefore <hi>Baronius</hi> ſpeaking of the entrie of <hi>Vigilius,</hi> calleth him a <hi>theife,</hi> a <hi>wolfe,</hi> a <hi>falſe Biſhop, an Antichrist:</hi> Yet ſoone after he calleth him the <hi>Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe he did not keepe promiſe in reſtoring <hi>Anthimius</hi> the Heretike. But therefore, as alſo for diuers greate crimes laide to his charge by the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anaſtaſ. in Vigilio.</note> he was apprehended, led violently away, the people perſuing him with <hi>curſings and Stones.</hi> He waſt caſt into priſon at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and then deliuered againe. While he was in the Citie, the fift generall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20781:14"/>Councell was held there: but he would not be preſent at it, leſt the dignity of the <hi>Roman</hi> chaire ſhould be impaired, if he ſate there: For firſt <hi>Menas</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. lib. de concil. c.</hi> 19.</note> and after him <hi>Euticheus</hi> Biſhop of the ſame See, preſided there. Neither doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> deme it. So <hi>Nicephorus</hi> ſaith when <hi>Eutichius</hi> was by the Emperour put in the roome of <hi>Menas</hi> lately deceaſed, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius, though agreeing with him in points of doctrine, yet refuſed to ſit by him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baron. an.</hi> 553.</note> But yet <hi>Baronius</hi> obſerueth that this <hi>Eutichius</hi> when he was choſen in the roome of <hi>Menas</hi> tendred the profeſſion of his faith vnto <hi>Vigilius:</hi> which though it were a thinge vſually practiſed amonge Biſhops, and <hi>Pelagius</hi> the next Pope did as much to the Biſhops of <hi>Italie,</hi> yet, as Popes and Papiſts take the matter, it gaue him power.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee that in almoſt all the yeares of the Gothes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the Pope had power to doe, and was ſeldom hindred, but oft times furthered by it. <hi>Pelagius</hi> the firſt, who ſucceeded <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilius,</hi> had the worſt time of it for a while; becauſe the Tirant <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilas</hi> then raged and triumphed in <hi>Rome,</hi> which he vnpeopled for 40. dayes: but he was ſoone vanquiſhed: and therefore the time of the Beaſts doeing was litle hindred by them: and conſequently he muſt needes be verrie neere his ende, &amp; may expire within 10. or 12. yeares; at leaſt within leſſe then 16. or 20. yeares from this preſent, or ſoone after; yea though his time of <hi>doeing</hi> began not till the dayes of <hi>Syricius</hi> or <hi>Innocent,</hi> becauſe the yeares may be <hi>Egyptian</hi> yeares, as ſome haue thought probable. Howſoeuer though he may endure to doe a <hi>litle longer,</hi> as ſome thinke, yet it doth not follow that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall ſtand ſoe longe; ſeeing it is in a manner cleare by the holy Scriptures, that he ſhall ſuruiue her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 16.</note> For after <hi>the</hi> fifth Angell hah <hi>powred</hi> his viall <hi>on the throne</hi> or ſeate of <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> and thereupon <hi>his Kingdom waxeth darke:</hi> by which deede (as ſome thinke) may be meant the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Rome, ſeeing that is the <hi>throne</hi> or ſeate, and by her ruin his Kingdom muſt of neceſſity <hi>waxe darke:</hi> becauſe it doth moſt of all conſiſt off, and reſt on the ſuppoſed chaire of <hi>Peter</hi> to remaine therefor euer; and a fond preſumption that the <hi>gates of hell</hi> ſhall neuer preuaile againſt that Church or Citie to roote it out; after theeſe things wee ſee the Beaſt ſuruiuing, and after the <hi>pouring</hi> out of the <hi>ſixth viall, the Beaſt ſendeth to gather the Kings,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.9.</note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20781:15"/>and they are gathered;</hi> but when the Citie ſhould be burned, <hi>they ſtand afarre off for feare of her torment,</hi> lamenting her ruin: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not then gathered when the Citie is beſeiged, but afterwards,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.</note> when they are <hi>gathered together</hi> with the Beaſt, <hi>to make warre with him that ſate on the horſe, and against his armie.</hi> Then they doe not ſtand afarre off, but <hi>are gathered</hi> together and <hi>ſlaine; and the fowles are filled with theire fleſh.</hi> This battaile therefore it ſeemes is after the racing of <hi>Babylon:</hi> and therefore I thinke that no man can giue any probable reaſon why <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire within leſſe then 10. yeares from this preſent yeare 1629. ſaue this only, that as yet he ſeeth not thoſe Kings in armes, and ſincerely endeauoring to doe it, that ſhould burne her.</p>
            <p>Here alſo hath beene ſome miſtaking aboute <hi>the hornes</hi> that ſhall deſtroy her: which ſome thinke to be tenne ſucceeding Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours: and they take <hi>Charles</hi> the 5. to be the firſt of theeſe. But beſides other good reaſons that might be alleadged to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, the preſent Emperours zeale to maintaine the Popiſh cauſe ſheweth this to be abſurd. Much better therefore doe they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, who take theeſe hornes to be all <hi>Chriſtians Kings, free Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> and that a certaine number is put for an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. For indeede this Beaſt hath vpon his tenne hornes, tenne feuerall Crownes; not one Crowne, but <hi>tenne;</hi> to ſhew that they are ſo many, or at leaſt a number of heads of ſeuerall Kingdoms and <hi>States:</hi> whereas the other Beaſt Reu. 12. which is the Ethnick Romane Empire, though it hath ſeauen <hi>Crownes</hi> on the <hi>ſeauen heads,</hi> to ſhew that thoſe were ſeauen ſeuerall ſucceeding formes of gouernment, of which the Emperours were one; yet that beaſt hath not tenne crownes one his <hi>hornes,</hi> becauſe thoſe tenne hornes were the tenne perſecutors, all Emperours or Kings of one Kingdom, haueing but one Crowne; as the hornes of the Beaſt in <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo were;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.22.</note> of which <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> was the litle horne. Which things, if they be well marked, proue that the hornes of the Popiſh beaſt were not at firſt 10. ſucceeding Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, who raiſed <hi>Romes</hi> Pope to his glorie; &amp; that the hornes that ſhall hate and burne her, are not 10. ſucceeding Emperours; but diuers Kings, free Princes and States, that ſhall at one and the ſame time doe it. Neither let any man thinke that <hi>Rome</hi> can not be ſhortly deſtroyed, becauſe many Kings, free Princes and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20781:15"/>States are yet obedient to the Pope and <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> For noe man can proue that all the hornes of the Beaſt <hi>ſhall hate the whore;</hi> or that all Chriſtian Kings ſhall fight againſt her: yea it is in a manner certaine that ſome of them ſhall continue with the Beaſt &amp; whore till the ende of the warre. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhould be burned wee ſee ſome Kings ſtanding <hi>afarre off,</hi> and weeping ouer her, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they doe not help her <hi>for ſeare of her torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t;</hi> as alſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the <hi>Beaſt gathereth,</hi> &amp; hath diuers Kings on his ſide, when he is taken &amp; deſtroied: theeſe without doubt are his freinds and helpers, and by conſequence may be ſome of the <hi>hornes:</hi> therefore though noe other King or Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be conuerted, yet <hi>Rome</hi> may be deſtroied by thoſe vvho already hate her. Neither ſhould the Saints feare the reſt, ſeeing the Scriptures ſhevv that <hi>they ſhall ſtand afarre of for feare,</hi> and not helpe her. Which doe not thinke to be vvritten, as if I ſaid that no other Kinge, State or Kingdom ſhall be conuerted, and ſoe brought to fight againſt her, but only thoſe vvho are already Proteſtants. For though God doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, for his greater glorie, performe greate vvorkes by ſmall meanes, and ouerthrovv the greateſt enemies by a ſmaller povver then they themſelues are; and that to ſome ſuch ende, he hath ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take away from the Proteſtant power, as he did from <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons</hi> armie, to ſhew what he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe by a few, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſtrength ſeemes to be brought to a low ebbe; and that it is therefore likely that he will alſo doe ſo in this deſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt; yea though now for theeſe many yeares noe <hi>King,</hi> State, or whole Nation haue yealded to be conuerted by the <hi>Word,</hi> and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is ſmall hope of any (vnles peraduenture of <hi>Venice</hi>) ſeeing they haue ſo longe withſtood the Word; yet it may pleaſe God to make any; yea that one of the Kings that ſhall doe this may be the Emperour then liueing, and that one of them may be the <hi>Angell of the throne;</hi> yet to ſay for certaine that he, or other Kings and States ſhall be conuerted, and ſhall ioyne therein, or that this or that <hi>Prince</hi> ſhall doe this thinge, ſauours to much of preſumption; ſeeing the Scriptures doe not name the perticular Kingdoms, nor any perticular man, as of old <hi>Ioſias</hi> in a like caſe 1. King. 13. therfore till theire owne inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the euent ſhew this thinge, noe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſay this <hi>Prince</hi> is that fift <hi>Angell;</hi> that other <hi>he that ſtandeth in the Sunne,</hi> viz. in the light and confidence of the Truth.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20781:16"/>
            <p>There haue beene ſome other miſtakings, which ſome haue cauſed by applying thoſe things of <hi>Daniel</hi> chap. 2.43.44. chap. 7.8.9. &amp;c. and eſpetially chap. 11.36. to the ende: and chap. 12. to the times of Antichriſt or of the Turkiſh Empire, &amp; thoſe that ſhould ſuffer vnder them; which indeede as
<note n="*" place="margin">M. Brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and Doc. Willet on Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</note> others proue doe note out the times of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> &amp; thoſe that followed ſoone after him: whoſe acts and times, as in a manner all confeſſe, are deſcribed chap. 11. ver. 21. to 36. and indeede the Propheſie of the things that he ſhould doe is certainly continued there, as may thus be proued. I. The Angell had there told <hi>Daniel</hi> of the miſeries which the Iewes ſhould ſuffer vnder <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.14. <hi>&amp; chap.</hi> 11.31. <hi>chap.</hi> 12.6.</note> who ſhould <hi>take away the daily Sacrifice, and ſet vp the abhomination, &amp;c.</hi> And queſtion is made, ſaying, <hi>How longe ſhall it be to the ende of theeſe wonders?</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time when all theeſe things ſhould be fulfilled is expreſſed chap. 12.11.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>From the time that the daily ſacrifice ſhall be taken away and the abhomination ſet vp, </hi> the dayes are ſummed to 1290. that is three yeares 7. monethes &amp; aboute 13. dayes: therefore theeſe things could belonge to noe other time, much leſſe to a time ſoe farre off, as that of the Pope or Turke.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The word <hi>Hamelech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 11.36.</note> this Kinge hath reference to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Hiſtorie: and the article <hi>ha</hi> is a note of demonſtration poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the Kinge before ſpoken of. Neither is there any likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that the Angel,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 10.14.</note> who came now to <hi>make him vnderstand what ſhould befall the Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 11.2.</note> and <hi>to tell him the truth of the viſions,</hi> would ſo ſodainly and at once, make ſuch a large ſtep, as is from the time of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> to Antichriſt, or the <hi>Turke,</hi> and that without telling <hi>Daniel,</hi> that now he would ſhew him another Kinge and Kingdom; which ſeeing he did not here, as he had donne concerning all the former
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See verſ.</hi> 2.3.4.5.6.7.10.</note> Kings and Kingdoms, both here and alſo chap. 8.20. it is plaine that he ſpeakes of the ſame Kinge and Kingdom: and ſo indeede whereas he had ſpoken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the Kings of the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> viz. <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> in theire ſeuerall ſucceſſions; and came at laſt to <hi>Antiochus Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> Kinge of the <hi>North,</hi> and his acts, both againſt the Kinge of the <hi>South,</hi> and alſo againſt the Iewes; he there without intermiſſion, or variation, continueth ſpeaking of them vnder the ſame titles verſ. 40. which is an infallible argument, that he continueth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20781:16"/>ſpeaking of the ſame Kinge, Kingdoms and times.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The ſequell of the Storie anſwereth to the Propheſie: for <hi>Antiochus</hi> did all this, as
<note n="*" place="margin">See D. Willet on Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel.</note> many haue proued out of the <hi>Maccabes,</hi> and other Hiſtories.</p>
            <p>Neither let any man thinke that Antichriſt can not be deſtroied till Chriſt come to iudgement; and that therefore it will be in vaine to beare armes againſt him, and his Supporters in theeſe times. For if it could be ſo that he ſhould ſtand till then; yet noe man can be ſure that the day is farre off or at hand. But it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the Scriptures, that thoſe words of Saint Paul,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Whome the Lord ſhall conſume with the Spirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightnes of his comming,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.14.15.17. <hi>&amp;c. verſ.</hi> 20.21. <hi>chap.</hi> 2.16.</note> muſt needes be meant of that comming, when <hi>the armies follow him.</hi> Reuel. 19. For then Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is deſtroyed, and then alſo Chriſt fighteth <hi>with the Spirit,</hi> or ſword of <hi>his mouth.</hi> So he ſaide of <hi>Pergamos,</hi> and the falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in her, <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly, and will fight against them with the ſword of my mouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.19.20. <hi>&amp; Rom.</hi> 11.26.</note> And ſo <hi>the deliuerer</hi> ſhall <hi>come to Sion,</hi> as Iſaiah ſhewes. It is moſt manifeſt, therefore I ſay that <hi>Saint Paul</hi> meaneth ſuch a bright comming againſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, both with the <hi>Word,</hi> and with the ſwords of Princes; and that he ſhall be wholly deſtroyed; as alſo that after his deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Nations <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall fight with the Saints,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 20.9.</note> and that before the day of iudgement. For the day of iudgement <hi>ſhall come as a theife in the night,</hi> and noe man can know before when it ſhall be:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.17.</note> but when <hi>the Angell ſtanding in the Sunne</hi> hath called many to the certaine deſtruction of Antichriſt, and his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters, euen <hi>to eate the fleſh of Kings, and the fleſh of Captaines &amp;c.</hi> and at the ſame time Antichriſt hath alſo called many to fight in his defence; Antichriſt is taken and deſtroyed: but if the World ſhould then haue an ende, then all who are called to this Battaile, at leaſt all that come againſt him, might know the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for they are called to the certaine deſtruction of him and his, <hi>to cate the fleſh of Kings &amp;c.</hi> but the whole World can not haue ſo ſure and viſſible a ſigne, of the ending of the World, ſeeing the Scriptures are contrarie herevnto, and ſhew that after this another battaile is fought with <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World can not then ende. The like might alſo be ſaide, when afterwards the <hi>Nations Gog</hi> &amp; <hi>Magog</hi> are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20781:17"/>in battaile againſt the Saints Reu. 20.7. if the world were to ende with that battaile the Saints that meete there, might know it before. But this they doe not know, therefore the world is not to ende at that time. Yet how ſoone after that it ſhall ende God only knoweth. It ſeemes that as the, Iſralites ſoone forgate his wonders in Egypt, ſo will thoſe that ſuruiue theeſe two battailes; and then, they beeing in ſecurity, the day will take them or theire poſteritie as a theife in the night. Soe that theeſe obiections doe not hinder but that all theeſe things may ſhortly be fulfilled; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially Romes <hi>Ruin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.</note> Wee muſt not thinke that Gods <hi>Spirit</hi> will <hi>alwaies ſtriue</hi> with that Church, noe more then he did with the old world; to whome he gaue 120. yeares time of repentance, <hi>when once the longe ſuffering of God waited, while the Arke was preparing, in the dayes of Noah;
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> a preacher of righteouſnes;</hi> and ſo indeede God hath now giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome well neere the like time ſince the preaching of <hi>Luther:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>an.</hi> 1517.</note> wherein God by him and others would haue <hi>cured Babel, but ſhe would not.</hi> Therefore when his longe ſuffering hath a like time <hi>waited,</hi> and they <hi>repent not to giue him glorie,</hi> her Ruin muſt needes approach and follow.</p>
            <p>And indeede the warres and other troubles that are already begun amonge many nations, ſhew that theeſe things are at hand, and namely that ere longe <hi>Rome</hi> the greateſt cauſe of them ſhall be deſtroied. The blood of the Saints ſhed in theeſe warres cries to heauen for ſpeedie vengeance on Pope &amp; <hi>Turke,</hi> but eſpetially and firſt of all on <hi>Rome,</hi> as the cauſe of all. For ſhe deuided the Empire into Eaſt &amp; weſt, and ſo made way for the <hi>Turke</hi> to enter by that diuiſion, and was therein the cauſe of all the ſlaughters which ſince haue beene made by <hi>Turkes</hi> vpon Chriſtians. It would aſke to much time to recko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp all the warres that ſhe hath cauſed, and the blood that ſhe hath otherwiſe ſhed in former times. To ſay nothing of the execrable practiſes of the bloodie inquiſition, if wee only looke on the warres of Chriſtendom in theeſe times, wee may finde that ſhe hath beene the increaſer if not the prouoker, and ſo beginner of them all. Call to minde vvhat her inſtruments the Ieſuits and Preiſts made the Emperour doe againſt the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> to make them reuolt, and ſoe to breede all thoſe vvarres there &amp; in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> to the cruell martyrdom of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Proteſtants, &amp; all ſtill by the animation &amp; encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20781:17"/>of the Pope and Romiſh Clergie. See what troubles and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they haue raiſed in <hi>Garmanie, France</hi> and the Low countries; and how eaſie will it be to finde her guiltie of all the blood, that hath of late beene ſhed in all theeſe places? and that therefore ſhe is like to be as dangerous to all that ſuruiue, if to preuent it, ſhe be not the ſooner deſtroyed? as it is written,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.6.</note> 
               <hi>The Woman was drunken with the blood of the Saints and of the Martyrs of Ieſus.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 18.24.</note> In her was found the blood of the Saints, and of all that were ſlaine vpon earth.</hi> And indeede they are ſtill ſo fierce in perſuite of blood, and haue ſo greate hope of bringing all Nations to the obedience of theire Pope and Church, that there is noe probabilitie, that they will euer giue ouer, till ſhe be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And he that will may ſee, that God hath therefore permitted her to goe on in this wickenes, to the ende that all true Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, all true Chriſtians, might be thereby moued in Chriſtian pitie, and for the ſaueing of Chriſtian blood (which otherwiſe ſhe will not ceaſe to ſhed) to combine theire forces to remoue her props, to weaken her greateſt Supporters, the howſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Polonian;</hi> and then to pull her downe: <hi>for her ſinnes haue reached vp to Heauen, and God hath remembred her wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</hi> Chriſt againſt whome they fight, as he alſo againſt them, hath as it were by all theeſe things ſaide to them that ſeeke peace with or for Papiſts, as <hi>Iehu</hi> to each meſſenger,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 9.18.</note> 
               <hi>What hast thou to doe with peace, turne thee behinde me;</hi> and concerning <hi>Rome,</hi> as he concerning <hi>Iezabel; Who is on my ſide, who?</hi> Yea God hath as it were by all theeſe things proclaimed warrs, and ſhewed that he will haue warres till ſhe be deſtroyed; and who then is able ſo to reſiſt his will, as without her <hi>Ruin</hi> to worke peace? For the Kings muſt deſtroy her, and the warrs mencioned Reu. 17.16. and chap. 19. can not be preuented. And therefore though the Proteſtants in all countries doe now ſeeme to be in more danger then <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt; yet it is marueilous to ſee how God hath begunne to prepare, &amp; fit all things to this worke. Firſt by ſuffering the Papiſts to prouoke Proteſtant <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> to it by theire warres, victories and practiſes. Secondly by taking away, or at leaſt binding and weakening the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedinent and danger; and indeede by weakening, or halfe pulling away her props. The greateſt impediment and danger that hath
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20781:18"/>euer beene ſuſpected is, that if Proteſtants and Papiſts ſhould fight one againſt another, the <hi>Turke</hi> would take that for an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to breake in vpon them &amp; endanger all Chriſtendom. But by the ill ſucceſſe, which was lately giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in <hi>Poland,</hi> his warres with the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and others, the lazines and indiſpoſition of his <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> the ſinewes of his warre, theire inſolencie and ſtubbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, who will now doe but what they liſt, the murder of <hi>Oſmond</hi> by them, the vnapt or rather fooliſh humours of <hi>Muſtepha</hi> that hath beene twiſe depoſed, and the childiſhnes of him that now raigneth, God hath as it were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the cauſe of that feare away: and while of late he hath ſuffered them to doe nothing againſt Chriſtendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worth the mentioning, he hath conuinced thoſe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and others in <hi>England</hi> and elſwhere of notorious flaterie &amp; trecherie who while the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and other proteſtant bulwarks were in danger, to get preferment by pleaſing the late Duke, his Mother and ſome others, hindred ſupplies and timely aide, by crying out againſt theeſe warres of Proteſtant againſt Papiſt, and ſaying it would bring in the <hi>Turke</hi> to get all. Which hath beene the cauſe of greate loſſes to Proteſtants: for in the meane while the howſe of <hi>Austria</hi> and the <hi>French Kinge</hi> preuailed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if the worſt ſhould come, viz. that the <hi>Turke</hi> ſhould attempt it, he can only endanger the Popiſh Princes that lie next him, and ſo keepe them buiſied that they ſhould not be able to reſcue <hi>Rome:</hi> neither is it likely that he could eaſely ouercome them. For <hi>Poland</hi> alone hath of late beene hard enough for him; and the <hi>Turke</hi> indeede is not ſo dangerous to our Religion as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, who doth daily ſtriue more by eagre warres and practiſes to ſubdue vs, then the <hi>Turke</hi> doth. Beſides the <hi>Turke</hi> ſuffers Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians to enioy theire religion in his dominions with leſſe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: the Papiſts in theire dominions put all Proteſtants to death or greate damages.</p>
            <p>God hath alſo in ſome reſpects pulled aſide and weakened the mightieſt props of <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt: as firſt the <hi>Emperour,</hi> who notwithſtanding all his Victories and ſtrength, is, in that reſpect, of ſupporting <hi>Rome,</hi> much weakened, becauſe he is in ſo much danger of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and of his owne diſcontented Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, Nobels, Huſbandmen and others, that he can not come to helpe her, for feare they ſhould in the meane while ioyne againſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20781:18"/>him with the much iniured Princes of <hi>Germanie;</hi> he beeing alſo farre off from <hi>Rome.</hi> The like may be ſaide of <hi>Poland;</hi> and in ſome ſort of <hi>France</hi> alſo. <hi>Italie</hi> is diuided amonge many Princes, moſt of them of ſmall force, and euer at diſcord. <hi>Venice</hi> the ſtrongeſt of them hath longe beene at variance with the Pope. The greate <hi>whore</hi> then hath but one greate prop, one greate ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter, namely the Kinge of <hi>Spaine,</hi> whoſe ſtate (as many haue
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sr. Fran. Bacon lo. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulam, his conſiderations touching a marre with</hi> Spanie.</note> proued) is nothing ſecure, but ſtands on ſliperie and diſunited grounds: againſt whome all Proteſtant Princes haue cauſe to fight as againſt one that ſeekes a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> to be vniuerſall Kinge, yea to ſupport the papacie, &amp; to bring all to his &amp; the Popiſh ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.3.4</note> 
               <hi>But he that helpeth &amp; he that is holpen ſhall both fall when God ſhall come downe to fight for Sion:</hi> And therefore when he ſhall pleaſe to weaken or remoue this Prop from ſupporting that See, the way lies open to <hi>Rome,</hi> and her finall ouerthrow. The vnited States haue do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne nobly againſt him, eſpetially of late in the <hi>Indies;</hi> and if others would as ſincerely ſtriue and indeanour to doe as much, it might ſoone be effected; at leaſt if the Ieſuited freinds of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spanie,</hi> that lurke in proteſtant States, were once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and expelled.</p>
            <p>All which things conſidered, I can not enough vvonder at the coldnes of this age, vvherein there are many, ſome alſo of greate auctority &amp; ſtrength, vvho knovv the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and ſee his Miniſters vvorking together and tiranizing, and yet are not moued to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this vvorke by the beſt meanes vvith Conſtancie, courage &amp; perſeuerance. Are not thoſe things fulfilled?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe iniquitie ſhall abound the loue of many ſhall waxe cold. All ſeeke theire owne, and no man that which is Christs;</hi> that ſo he alone might raigne in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters: ſeeing nothing indeede but the deſtruction of Rome can vvorke this, or giue peace and felicitie to the Church, as all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſee, vvho either looke diligently into the Scriptures or into the practiſes of the enemies; and how Princes are anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Romiſh Spirits: yet I confeſſe that this can not eaſely be donne till the Kings of <hi>Spanie</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> her cheifeſt props and champions, be firſt vveakened, and put in feare of her torment; vvhich (indeede vvill make them ſtand a far off, and ſoe) is a part of the vvorke. But vvhen ſhe is deſtroied, a <hi>greate multitude crie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.6.</note> Alleluia: For the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20781:19"/>
            <p>And will they then be ſlack in giueing theire moneyes, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, labours, counſailes or conſents to this worke? The Papiſts are not ſo in theire warre againſt vs. The Pope beſtoweth his falſe bleſſings on them, and they ſhew theire greate thankfulnes for theeſe falſe benefits, in fighting manfully to adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and giueing moneyes and other helpes to further the ſame. Chriſt hath beſtowed more, yea greater and truer benefits on vs, euen all wee haue in heauen and earth, by them to binde vs to be as true vnto him: and who then can eſcape his wrath, that is not faithfull and thankfull?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19. <hi>chap.</hi> 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekia</hi> was in danger of enemies, and after <hi>ſicke vnto the death: And the Lord ſaued Hezekia:
<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.25.</note> But He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekia rendred not againe according to the benefit donne vnto him: for his heart was lifted vp, therefore there was wrath vpon him, and vpon Iudah and Ieruſalem.</hi> He hearkened to the flatteries of the <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> the enemies of God, was to conuerſant with them, and did not refuſe them, and truſt in God who ſaued him; which was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 16.7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> A fault that was alſo in <hi>Aſa,</hi> who at firſt relied on the Lord, and was mightely deliuered: afterwards he <hi>relyed on the Kinge of Syria,</hi> and not on the Lord, and was therefore puniſhed with warres. Who then would not be more thankfull, and cleaue more faſt vnto Chriſt, then Papiſts doe to the Pope? and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that follow Chriſt ſhall aſſuredly be Victors. Reu. 17.14. chap. 19.18.20.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>For the eyes of the Lord runne to and fro throughout the whole earth to ſhew himſelfe ſtronge in the behalfe of them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tortus. pag.</hi> 51.</note> whoſe heart is perfit toward him.</hi> Tortus ſaith, <hi>In our ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall birth in baptiſme wee are to conceiue of a ſecret and implied oath, which wee take at our new birth to yeelde obedience to the ſpirituall Prince, which is Christs Vicar.</hi> As if he ſaide that in theire Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme they receiued the marke of the Beaſt: for
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Chriſtian. pag.</hi> 282. <hi>&amp;</hi> 296.</note> that is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and obey his law, as on the contrarie to receiue, obey and profeſſe Gods Word is to haue Gods marke: but wee are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the name of the Trinitie, not of the Pope: And if they thinke that they owe ſo much to the Pope, what owe wee to God and his Chriſt? What owe wee to our Sauiour, and our Brethren which are members of his myſticall body? When wee were baptized wee receiued the promiſe, and conſequently the marke of God, promiſing to <hi>fight manfully vnder his Banner againſt</hi> all his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20781:19"/>enemies, and to be <hi>Christs faithfull Seruants and Souldiers vnto our liues ende,</hi> ſuch as <hi>truſt</hi> in him that he ſhall ouercome all enemies.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let not Princes therefore be like them that <hi>goe downe to Egypt for helpe, and ſtay on horſes, and trust in Charets:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.1.2.3.4.</note> but looke not to the holy one of Iſrael, neither ſeeke the Lord: yet he is alſo wiſe, and will bringe euill, and not call back his words.</hi> Let therefore noe Proteſtant Prince ſeeke leauge with Papiſts, as <hi>Aſa</hi> did with <hi>Syrians,</hi> who thereby diſpleaſed the Lord, as alſo by relying on them. For the Papiſts as <hi>the Egyptians are men and not God, and theire horſes fleſh and not ſpirit: When the Lord ſhall ſtretch out his hand, both he that helpeth ſhall fall, and he that is holpen: for the Lord of hosts ſhall come downe to fight for Mount Sion,</hi> Let vs therefore looke into the Word of God, and ſee what God would haue to be donne againſt them; not to ioyne firſt (againſt the <hi>Turke</hi>) with them, who haue the <hi>marke</hi> of the Beaſt. Doth Chriſt ſeeke the helpe of his enemies? that is, the helpe of Antichriſt, or of them who haue the <hi>marke</hi> of the Beaſt? there can be noe more ſafety, nor good in mingling and ioyning with them, then was vnto the Iſraelites <hi>in mingling with the heathen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.28.85.</note> and in ioyning <hi>vnto Baal Peor,</hi> or with the Egyptians: Iſa. 30.2. And if Papiſts ioyne with Proteſtants, they will worke, and haue hope to bringe them to theire religion: they are verrie ſubtill in perſwading, working a thouſand wayes, and will not ſticke to compell, if it lie in theire power. They vvould caſt to haue the Generall of theire religion: and if they could be perſvvaded to fight vnder a Proteſtant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, yet the Scriptures ſhevv that in Chriſts armie, there ſhall be none that haue the <hi>marke</hi> of the Beaſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 19.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>for they that are with him are called, and choſen and faithfull.</hi> They <hi>follow him clothed in fine linnen, white &amp; cleane: and haue his Fathers name written in theire forheads;</hi> and conſequently are not Papiſts, defiled with the <hi>marke</hi> &amp; name of the Beaſt. Neither ſhall there be any Papiſts in Chriſts warre againſt the Turke, when he is ouerthrowen. For as I ſhewed the Saints doe firſt fight againſt the Beaſt, and the Kings with him: the Beaſt, and the Kings and people that are with him are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen; ſome of them are ſlaine in battaile,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 19.23.</note> the Beaſt and falſe Prophet are <hi>taken: but the remnant were ſlaine with the ſword of him that ſate vpon the horſe: which ſword proceedeth out of his mouth:</hi> that is conuerted to Chriſt by his Word.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:20781:20"/>
            <p>And then and not before they come to be of Chriſts armie againſt the Turke chap. 20. therefore Chriſt vvill not haue Proteſtants to ioyne vvith Papiſts againſt the Turke, but rather to ioyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues firſt againſt Antichriſt &amp; his, aftervvards againſt the Turke, neither can mortall man be vviſer then God, that they ſhould finde a better vvay then God hath determined &amp; reuealed; vvho out of doubt vvill neuer proſper any other contrarie deſigne, how religiouſly ſoeuer it may ſeeme to be vndertaken.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee they indeauour wholly to roote out all Proteſtants, to come into Chriſts inheritance, where he raigneth, and that where the Lord was lately ſerued, there the Pope is now worſhipped, idollatrie erected, and our Brethren afflicted with miſerie and death; neither are they moued to helpe rightly and ſpeedily, whoſe duty it is: which pleaſeth the Papiſts, that ſo when ſuch haue ſuffered theire Brethren to periſh, they may alſo roote out them. Which I write not to ſtirre vp any priuate man to lift vp his hand againſt any perticular Papiſt whatſoeuer; nor yet to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Subiects of theeſe <hi>Popiſh Tirants</hi> to riſe, and fight for theire religion after the exemple of the Iewes vnder <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes:</hi> of whome it is ſaide,
<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32</note> 
               <hi>the people that doe know theire God ſhall be ſtronge and doe exploits.</hi> I rather wiſh them to ſuffer, and waite his leiſure, who ſaith,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay:</hi> as he hath denounced againſt theeſe <hi>Tirants,</hi> the Champions of Antichriſt, ſaying,
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>He that leadeth into captiuitie ſhall goe into captiuitie: he that killeth with the ſword muſt be killed with the ſword. Here is the patience and the faith of the Saints.</hi> Patience in waiting for this, and faith in beleeuing it; rather yelding to ſuffer, then to receiue the <hi>marke</hi> of the Beaſt, as chap. 14.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 14.12</note> 
               <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints; here are they that keepe the commandements of God, and the faith of Ieſus.</hi> But if ye, ô Princes and States, in whoſe power it is to helpe theeſe afflicted ones, be true Proteſtants and Seruants of Chriſt, thinke the Lord doth as it were aſke you, whether they that thus afflict Gods Seruants be of Chriſts armie or noe? ye will anſwer, they are not; but rather of Antichriſts armie, haueing the marke of the Beaſt in theire right hand, and bearing armes againſt Chriſt; then by conſequence, they who ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerly reſiſt, if they be not ſubiects to the <hi>Tirants,</hi> but free, are of Chriſts armie, and Chriſt is with them: and without doubt, all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20781:20"/>men of ripe yeares, if it be in theire power to be of either, are of one of theeſe armies; there is no meane betweene; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me.</hi> And that will ſuch finde in the day of the Lord, when he
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall come to giue euery man as his worke ſhall be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the meane while, whether or no, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee ſay that wee loue our Chriſtian <hi>Brethren,</hi> yea or God himſelfe? yet wee ſay,
<note n="e" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>wee loue him, becauſe he first loued vs.</hi> But S. Iohn ſaith,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Hereby perceiue wee the loue of God, becauſe he laide downe his life for vs, and wee ought to lay downe our liues for the brethren.</hi> See what <hi>Abraham</hi> did,
<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.14</note> 
               <hi>when he heard that his brother was taken captiue, he armed his trained Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, brought again his brother</hi> Lot, <hi>and his goods, the women alſo and the people.
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29.</note> And if ye be Chriſts, then are ye Abrahams ſeede.
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.38.</note> If ye were Abrahams children, ye would doe the workes of Abraham.</hi> Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat likewiſe
<note n="k" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 3.7.</note> helped <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt the <hi>Moabits.</hi> Religion &amp; the profeſſours thereof were in danger; wherefore he ſaide vnto <hi>Iehoram,
<note n="l" place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 16.9.</note> I will goe vp; I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horſes as thy horſes.</hi> He truſted in God, and he proſpered therin. <hi>For the eyes of the Lord runne to and fro throughout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelfe ſtronge in the behalfe of them whoſe heart is perfit tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards him.</hi> They that ceaſe to truſt in him, and rather rely on the helpe and alliance of his enemies, them he forſakes, as wee ſee in <hi>Aſa,</hi> who <hi>relyed on the Kinge of Syria.</hi> But <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> helped his brethren, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did. He thought it not enough to ſay, I am a Prince of peace, if I may haue peace with the enemies, why ſhould I hazard my owne to helpe others? it ſtands not with pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecie. For if ſuch excuſes would haue ſerued;
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>the inhabitants of Meroz</hi> could haue ſaide much for themſelues, as that they loued peace, &amp; abhorred the ſheeding of blood, and ſought theire owne ſafety. But if the enemy knowing they will not fight be therefore the more emboldened to deſtroy theire brethren firſt, that they may afterwards deſtroy them, then this wilfull peace is rather merciles crueltie to theire brethren and to themſelues, then true charitie to any. For enemies haue moſt deſire to fight with them whome they perceiue to be faint hearted, as aſſured that they ſhall thereby preuaile. Therefore ſuch polecie is rather extreame folly than true vviſdom: becauſe God loues not, but forſakes them vvho forſake him or theire brethren.
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>My heart is towards the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20781:21"/>Gouernours of Iſrael that offered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues willingly amonge the people.
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> Zebulun</hi> and <hi>Nephtali were a people that ieoparded theire liues vnto the death in the high places of the field,</hi> viz. to helpe the Lord and theire brethren, and were therefore bleſſed: <hi>Meroz</hi> did not ſoe, and was therefore
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed,</hi> as guiltie of blood that might haue beene ſpilt, and as one not regarding the crie of the <hi>afflicted.</hi> But God
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>pſa.</hi> 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>when he maketh inquiſition for blood he remembreth them: he forgetteth not the crie of the afflicted.</hi> Will not he then finde ſuch as neglect them guiltie? for as a famous Diuine ſaith,
<note n="r" place="margin">B. Hall. Contemp. the Reſcue of Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beon.</note> 
               <hi>Euen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in thoſe things wee may remedy, makes vs no leſſe actors then conſent; ſome men kill as much by looking on, as others by ſmiting: wee are guiltie of all the euill wee might haue hindred.</hi> And indeede the holy Ghoſt ſaith;
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>pro.</hi> 24.10.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>If thou faint in the day of aduerſity, thy ſtrength is ſmall. If thou forbeare to deliuer them that are drawen vnto death, and thoſe that are readie to be ſlaine: If thou ſaieſt, behold wee knew it not: doth not he that pondereth in the heart conſider it? and he that keepeth thy ſoule doth he not know it? and ſhall not he render vnto euery man according to his worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It therefore behooueth him to ſtirre who either regardeth his owne ſaluation, or Gods protection. Let them therefore, who may giue helpe, take heede while there is time; eſpetially ſeeing the cauſe is common to all, and not God and ciuill pollecie only, but euen common ſenſe teacheth this with the Poët, <hi>Ecquid</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad te post paulò ventura pericula ſentis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nam tua res agitur paries cum proximus ardet.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſaying is the more to be regarded, becauſe he that will may know, that the Spaniſh Kinge who is called <hi>Catholick,</hi> aimeth at the Catholick gouernment. Howſoeuer what will he and they not doe for the <hi>Catholicke</hi> cauſe, as they call it, who are gouerned by the Pope, Rome, and the Ieſuits and Preiſts? or who haue the marke of the Beaſt, and conſequently are led by the deuill and his Agents?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>theeſe frogs and</hi> locuſts <hi>are Spirits of deuils.</hi> Are they not then, as much to be truſted in any thinge they pretend, as of old <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> the <hi>Syrian Kinge,</hi> who came in peaceablie to the Subiects of another Kingdom, and with gifts and flatteries wrought them
<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.26</note> to betray it, namely Egypt? of whome therefore it was ſaide,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 8.25.</note> 
               <hi>By peace he ſhall deſtroy many.
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 11.23.24.</note> After the leauge made with him, he ſhall worke deceitefully, for he ſhall come vp, and ſhall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20781:21"/>become ſtronge with a ſmall people: He ſhall enter peaceablie: and ſcatter amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pray and riches: and he ſhall forecaſt his deuiſes againſt the ſtronge holds for a time;</hi> viz. till he had corrupted the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> raiſed factions amonge them, and ſo prepared them to betray the Kingdom to the greate armie he intended to bringe, and which he after
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 25.</note> brought: alſo touching his craft to obtaine <hi>Iudea,</hi> and ouerthrow religion there;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 30.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>He ſhall haue intelligence with them that forſake the holy couenant. And ſuch as doe wickedly againſt the couenant ſhall he corrupt by flatteries.</hi> Wherein he and they were liuely types of Antichriſt and his inſtruments, and of his ſecret freinds that are falſe brethren in other Churches and States.</p>
            <p>Now therefore if any man thinke that Papiſts are more ſincere in theire pretences to Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; let him remember what doctrine the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> left them, <hi>fidem Haereticis non ſeruandam:</hi> yea let him reade <hi>Nauar.</hi> in <hi>Manual.</hi> cap. 12. num. 18. cap. 21. &amp; <hi>Sam. Aphor.</hi> tit. <hi>de teſtibus;</hi> and then tell me, whether they thinke it lawfull to equiuocate, and delude Hereticks with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telties? at leaſt for the Catholick cauſe? and how longe they are to be truſted, I would he would iudge whome it moſt concerneth: and eſpetially ſeeing God hath ſeemed to haue lately warned vs of ſuch dangers: I doe not meane ſo much by ſignes &amp; prodegies, as by that which they haue donne to our brethren in other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and prouinces. Howſoeuer wee know that the Pope, and his thinke and affirme
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Symancha. inſtit. cathol. cap.</hi> 45. <hi>num.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; Allan againſt the execution of Iuſtice, c.</hi> 5.</note> that warre vndertaken for the cauſe of religion is without controuerſie lawdable and good;
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thuan. hiſt. lib.</hi> 42. <hi>ad ann.</hi> 1585. <hi>lib.</hi> 62. <hi>and lib.</hi> 63. <hi>ad ann.</hi> 1577. <hi>&amp; Symanch. inſtit. Cathol. cap.</hi> 45. <hi>num.</hi> 15. <hi>Platin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in vita Greg,</hi> 7.</note> that peace is not te be made, nor kept with Hereticks: yea they ſay that the Pope hath right <hi>Imperia, regna, principatus, &amp; quicquid habere mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tales poſſunt auferre &amp; dare;</hi> and that to <hi>whome he will</hi> as he ſaith; and blaſphemouſly he for this thinge abuſeth that place Ier. 5.10. as <hi>Hadrian</hi> in an Epiſtle to the Archbiſhops of <hi>Treueire, Mentz, and Colen, whence had the Emperour the Empire but from vs? Behold the Empire is in our power to giue is to whome wee will. For therefore are wee of God ſet ouer nations, and Kingdoms to deſtroie, to plucke vp, to build and to plant.</hi> What he, and his beeing of the ſame body and opinion haue donne in theeſe times, and daily goe aboute, there is no neede to tell; the matter it ſelfe declareth, and that in many countries. Such is theire induſtrie; who (as wee may well thinke) will by theire tounges, ſubtelties, gifts, hands and feete
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20781:22"/>doe all things that they can for theire religion &amp; brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; whome alſo wee know without commandement from God to endeauour with all poſſible labour night and day, &amp; to venture theire verrie liues to proffit the Pope &amp; Church of Rome, and to roote out the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; although in all theeſe things, they to theire euerlaſting damnation profoundlie take the marke of the Beaſt in theire for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and in theire hands. And ſhall not wee then be content to goe forth for Chriſt, and vnder Chriſt to doe as much as they, while wee may both benefit the Church of Chriſt, and ſecure our ſelues? the voice ſaith of the <hi>whore ſitting on many waters;
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.</note> reward her as ſhe hath rewarded you.</hi> Behold then what they doe, &amp; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and then if thou beeſt a ſincere Chriſtian thou wilt ſay, ſhall they doe theeſe things vnpuniſhed? theeſe things are all donne &amp; vndertaken not only out of coueteouſnes, or in a deſire of rule, but alſo for the Pope and Church of Romes ſake, yea for the <hi>Clergies</hi> ſake; and indeede by theire vnceſſant inſtigations: but when the cauſe why they doe theeſe things ſhall be taken away, theeſe will ceaſe, peace will enſue, and Chriſt ſhall raigne alone in ſpirituall matters.</p>
            <p>Wee knovv alſo that all things vvhich the Pope and his doe againſt vs for religion ſake, are verrie much againſt Chriſt, as the Scriptures declare. Wee may know alſo, if vvee vvill how greate authority Chriſt hath giuen vnto his, eſpetiallie vnto Kings and States to take from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Beaſt theire vvealth, and not only to eate her fleſh, but alſo the fleſh of her freinds Reuel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19.17. and that verrie iuſtly; becauſe many of our Brethren haue beene by them led captiue and ſlaine: for as the Lord vvould haue the deedes of <hi>Ameleck</hi> remembred, and recompenſed Exod. 17.14. and 1. Sam. 15. ſo he ſaith concerning theeſe men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>If any man haue an eare let him heare. He that leadeth into captiuitie, ſhall goe into captiuitie: He that killeth with the ſword, muſt be killed with the ſword.</hi> And therefore though they haue no auctoritie to take from the follovvers of Chriſt; yet they vvhich are Chriſts, ought to doe his commandements againſt thoſe his enemies; and vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theeſe things can be donne vvithout loſſe to any ſaue <hi>Rome</hi> only, as alſo vvhether they that haue power ſhould feare to doe his commandements, and what it is to haue communion vvith ſo greate enemies, the props of the Whore and Antichriſt, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20781:22"/>2. Corinth. 6.14. Deuter. 7. vvhat it is to ſtand afarre off, and not to fight vnder Chriſts <hi>Standart,</hi> let any true Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian iudge, ſeeing as a greate Prelate ſaide in a like caſe,
<note n="a" place="margin">Epiſe. Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Tortura Tort. in Epiſ. Dedica.</note> 
               <hi>This cauſe is of that kinde wherein when a man gathereth not with Christ, he ſcatereth with Christs aduerſarie, where vnleſſe one deliuer the faith, neither ſhall he deliuer his Soule.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Now when the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe is brought into danger, let noe man be a ſpectatour, but euerie one an actour: and where the cauſe of all men is handled, there with all power and labour, with all ſtuddie and indeauour to ſkirmiſh ſtoutly for it. And herein in what low ſtate ſoeuer a man be, yet let him be a Christian.</hi> The cauſe of religion is in danger; and if they that profeſſe the ſame religion helpe not, what religion the while is there in them? The name <hi>Religion</hi> commeth of a word that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth to binde, and it is a ſpirituall bond, whereby the men of each profeſſion are bound one vnto another, and knit faſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in faith and loue, as one body. In the true religion they are knit together vnder Chriſt, and are both bound vnto him theire head, and alſo vnto one another, as true members of the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Is any member then of Chriſts body in danger, and will not all the reſt helpe? He that will not helpe is he a member? doth he not cut himſelfe off from the body, if he ſtand like a newter? when <hi>Iabeſh Gilead</hi> was in danger, and the enemie ſought
<note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2.7.</note> to <hi>lay it for a reproch vpon all Iſraell; the feare of the Lord fell on the people, and they came out as one man:</hi> as one body; euery man ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a true member: there vvas true Religion. As therefore Chriſt counted himſelfe touched vvhen his members vvere tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Act. 9.4. ſo ought it to be amonge the members of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, vvho vvhen one is in danger ſhould all make it theire ovvne caſe, and helpe vvhat they can.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.27.</note> 
               <hi>Pure religion and vndefiled before God is this,</hi> to helpe the diſtreſſed <hi>in theire affliction.</hi> True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are novv the <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aell</hi> of God; the diuers Nations, are but as the ſeuerall tribes; they ſhould be all knit together vnder one head, viz. vnder Chriſt, and that to fight againſt Antichriſt, vvho now raigneth. Is any member then in danger, and vvill not all the reſt helpe? he that can helpe and will not, is he a member? <hi>Ioſhua</hi> doth greately praiſe the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> and the <hi>Gadites,</hi> and the <hi>halfe tribe of Manaſſeh,</hi> when he ſaith to them,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 22.1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Ye haue not left youre Brethren theeſe many dayes vnto this day, but haue kept the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20781:23"/>charge of the commandement of the Lord youre God.</hi> There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who call themſelues Proteſtants; and yet how few that truly deſire this praiſe by proteſting ſincerely againſt the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and his members, who beare his marke, and fight ſtoutely for him, and for one another?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Kings of the earth band themſelues, and the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers take counſell together againſt the Lord and againſt his Anointed.</hi> Doe thoſe who profeſſe themſelues Seruants of Chriſt, doe as much for Chriſt, and for one another? as yet they haue not. Chriſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>luk.</hi> 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>The children of this world are in theire generation wiſer then the children of light.</hi> I would to God they were not alſo more zealous and bold for theire Maiſter. Doe wee not ſee what miſcheife the freinds of Antichriſt daily put in practiſe againſt the Seruants of Chriſt, and how the Pope approues of theeſe deedes? And how longe they who haue the marke of the Beaſt, are gouerned by the Pope, and led by the Ieſuits are to be truſted in any thinge that they prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I hartely wiſh that they would iudge whome it moſt of all concerneth. In the meane time wee muſt pray as Pſal. 74. <hi>Haue respect vnto the couenant:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.20.</note> for the darke places of the earth are full of the habitations of crueltie.</hi> And as Iſa. 63. &amp; 15. to chap. 65.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our aduerſary the Deuill,</hi> who allwayes <hi>goes aboute like a roaring Lion, ſeeking whome he may deuoure,</hi> without all doubt labours ſo much the more when he knowes that he hath but a litle time for the Beaſt, and Whore and <hi>Dragon.</hi> He will labour to haue his Agents in all Courts and Kingdoms, that they may by all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts, proiects and deuiſes that may be inuented make ſome fight openly, and others worke ſecretly for the Beaſt and Whore; but eſpetially that they may vnder colour of wiſdom, keepe ſuch as are beſt able from aiding theire brethren, or fighting againſt the Whore and her props; that ſo noe man of power may ſeeke to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill Gods will in aiding the Church, or ruinating the Kingdom of the Beaſt, but rather forſake the Spouſe of Chriſt, and leaue her members in danger of the aduerſaries; that ſo Papiſts may by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees recouer or deſtroy all. To this ende, he will labour vvhat he can to get aduantage out of all diſpoſitions and affections; as of old out of the diſpoſition and affection of <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> a Kinge benigne, munificent, credulous, voide of ſuſpition, greately lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueing &amp; truſting his Seruants. The deuill therefore labours that <hi>Haman</hi> might be in grace: becauſe he knew that no man would
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20781:23"/>contradict him that ſhould be moſt in fauour with the Kinge, but rather that euerie one would be readie to flatter him in all things whatſoeuer he goes aboute; and that therefore he might make the Kinge beleeue that his beſt ſubiects the Iewes, were the Kings greateſt enemies; and that to this ende, that whereas at that time God was aboute to do ſome good for his people the Iewes then in captiuity, he might by this <hi>Haman</hi> wholly deſtroy the Iewes, and ſo not only fruſtrate Gods benignitie, and the reſtauration of true religion; but alſo by this meanes wholly deſtroy the Kinge, by cauſeing that for his iniuſtice and crueltie God might be his enemie. Neuertheleſſe <hi>Haman</hi> vſed a pretext, ſaying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther.</hi> 8.3.</note> 
               <hi>It is not for the Kings proffit, or honour, to ſuffer them:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, they are againſt the Kings prerogatiue; for he ſaith, <hi>theire lawes are diuers from all people, neither keepe they the Kings lawes;</hi> (ſo others pretend Ezra. 4.12. Dan. 3. chap. 6.13.) yea <hi>Haman</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that the ſlaughter would be verrie proffitable to the Kinge; whereas on the contrarie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>if they had beene ſold for bondme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, the enemie could not counteruaile the Kings damage;</hi> ſo good Subiects were they, and proffitable to the <hi>Kinge;</hi> neuertheleſſe by this meanes he had preuailed with the Kinge, if God had not turned it: ſo powerfull was the man whome the Kinge did to much loue; and that the Deuill knew well enough, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he vvas an inſtrument the fitter for ſuch a worke; although indeede his life was moſt dangerous, &amp; his death moſt proffitable to the Kinge, according to that;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.5.</note> 
               <hi>Take away the wicked from before the Kinge, and his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, otherwiſe it ſtands in danger. As <hi>Rehoboam</hi> found,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vvho vvas led by the counſell of the vvicked younge men <hi>to ſpeake roughly to the people.</hi> The Deuill knew vvel enough that the ſtrength of the King, did vnder God, moſt of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in the loue of the people, vvho vvhen they loue, and are loued vvill giue theire ſubſtance and liues for him: the Deuill therefore ſought to alienate the heart of the <hi>Kinge</hi> from the people, and thereby the heart of the people from the Kinge; that ſo the Kingdom diuided in it ſelfe might not ſtand, but might lie open to diuiſion, and thereby to the Gentiles, and ſo that by that meanes the true Religion might alſo be quite put out. And wee may be ſure that he hath now ſo laboured &amp; ſtill will to doe the like againſt religion in Proteſtant <hi>Kingdoms</hi> &amp; <hi>States.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:20781:24"/>
            <p>So alſo when God was aboute to reedifie the Citie &amp; Temple,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>and chap.</hi> 6.</note> the Diuell raiſed vp ſcorners and ſlanderers againſt the builders, that they might hinder the worke. And when <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was aboute a good worke,
<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Satan ſtood at his right hand to hinder him.</hi> So when God vvas
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>aboute to deliuer Iſrael by Sampſon;</hi> the Deuill and the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> raiſed vp a <hi>Delilah to hinder</hi> him. And his induſtrie is indeede alwayes ſo greate, that vvho can looke for better fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in theeſe times? Howſoeuer wee ſee what Antichriſt doth daily practiſe againſt Chriſt, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are his; how alſo he keepes the people in blindneſſe, and hinders the true preaching &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods Word, &amp; therein Chriſts raigne; yea how the cauſe of the Goſpel doth euery where ſeeme to go backwards, &amp; the cauſe of <hi>Rome</hi> to waxe luſtie: yet few are moued to ſeeke a right remedie. They who are outwardly Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, inwardly Papiſts, they deſire to rectifie all things, &amp; vnder pretext of greate zeale &amp; wiſdom, they ſtill ſeeke ſuch an excelent remedy as ſhall in ſhew promiſe greate redreſſe, yet ſhall indeede come to no ende, but ſpend in vaine time, treaſure and labour, giue the Papiſts opportuintie of enlarging theire bounds, make proteſtants be glad of peace on hard conditions, &amp; bringe the proteſtant cauſe into a much worſe ſtate; this beeing brought aboute, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appeares what was indeede the drift of theire deſignes. They that are lukewarme, and ſeeke theire owne, not that which is Chriſts, theeſe are willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue; they will not contradict the former, but ſerue the times what euer they be; others haue a deſire to ſpeake, but there is no place for them amonge Princes; others haue both place and will, but they are affraide; to ſuch a one the holy Ghoſt ſaith;
<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>If thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together holdest thy peace at this time, then ſhall there enlargement and deliuerance ariſe to the people of God from another place, but thou and they Fathers howſe ſhall be destroied.</hi> How greate is the coldnes? but why doe wee wonder? when as it ſeemeth in the time of greateſt danger, the coldneſſe ſhould be ſo greate, that the Angell <hi>ſtanding in the Sunne,</hi> ſhould haue neede to <hi>crie with a loude voice:</hi> as if men feared whether they might for Chriſts cauſe hurt his enemies; peraduenture not allowing the cauſe of Religion to be a ſufficient cauſe of warre, although the aduerſaries neither haue beene, nor are ſo ſcrupulous; and God hath ſaide of the <hi>Whore, ſerue her, as ſhe hath ſerued</hi> you; peraduenture pretending alſo that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20781:24"/>if this vvere granted, the aduerſaries vvould alſo openly ſay the ſame things for themſelues; (the Diuell, the Pope &amp; Papiſts vvill deſire and indeauour that vvee may alvvayes be of that minde, that in the meane time, they who are otherwiſe affected may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile ouer vs all:) but in the meane while theeſe men, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues Proteſtants are vnwilling to ſee that warre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken as matters ſtand at this day both with our brethren, with the faith it ſelfe, yea &amp; with our ſelues alſo, might rather be called defenſiue
<note n="*" place="margin">S. Francis Bacon Lo. Verulam his Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Touching a warre with Spaine.</note> and preuentiue then offenſiue; the zeale and Ieſuited Spirits of the aduerſaries giueing all proteſtant Princes &amp; States, ſoe iuſt cauſe of feare and preuenting care. Neuertheleſſe when our ſeeming proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to maſke &amp; palliate theire owne trecherie in religion, or at leaſt to couer theire owne lukewarmenes and cowardiſe, call this warre ignominious and the perſwaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a Ieſuiticall doctrine, they doe not, or will not ſee, that this is to condemne thoſe noble Kings and theire acts, who ſhall make the whore deſolate and naked, and burne her with fire; Is not that a warre vndertaken for religion ſake, and for Chriſts cauſe?</p>
            <p>Let them therefore remember that there is greate difference, betweene thoſe who are of the true religion, and thoſe who only affirme, or thinke themſelues to be ſuch, betweene thoſe who know that they ſhall fight againſt the enemies of Chriſt, and thoſe who only pretend, or imagin this thinge; betweene thoſe vvho are moued to vvarre for the Popes, and Church of Romes ſake, and thoſe vvho are moued thereto, for Chriſts and theire owne ſafeties ſake; betweene thoſe who receiue the marke of the Beaſt, haue his name: for it ſeemes in theire mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theire Armies are called Catholick Armies, and themſelues Catholicks, that is vniuerſals of theire ruler the Pope, who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Catholick or Vniuerſall Biſhop;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.19.</note> in many things Chriſt beareth <hi>no rule ouer</hi> them, therefore they are <hi>not called by</hi> his <hi>name,</hi> at leaſt not rightly: yea betweene them that murther the Seruants of Chriſt, and thoſe who beare the marke of the liueing God, follow and obey him by rooting out his enemies to the glorie of God, and the libertie of the Church; laſtly betweene them who are hereto allured by the Beaſt and falſe Prophet, and gathered together by the ſpirits of Deuils, working myracles; and thoſe who are commanded of God concerning the whore
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20781:25"/>ſitting on many waters; <hi>Reward her, as ſhe hath rewarded you, double vnto her double, &amp;c.</hi> And if this be as Deut. 7. yet Chriſt who is theire leader doth
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.11.14.</note> in <hi>righteouſnes iudge and make warre;</hi> they are no better to him then cananites: and his Seruants follow him vpon <hi>white</hi> horſes, clothed in fine linnen white, and <hi>cleane.</hi> The blood therefore of theeſe his enemies doth not defile them. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any ouercome him who ouercommeth the Kings, becauſe he is
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord of Lords, and Kinge of Kings, and they that are with him are called &amp; choſen, and faithfull.</hi> There is therefore no danger or cauſe why theeſe Seruants of Chriſt ſhould feare to fight, leaſt they ſhould be vanquiſhed in warre, ſeeing vnto them the Lord hath
<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 16.10 <hi>chap.</hi> 17.14. <hi>chap.</hi> 18.10. <hi>chap.</hi> 19.18.</note> aſſured victorie, and to theire aduerſaries deſtruction. He that hath promiſed this thinge is theire Leader, and
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</note> he is <hi>called Faithfull and true.</hi> He will ſurely do it. Wee haue his word for this thinge. And
<note n="t" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</note> if <hi>wee beleeue not, yet he abideth faithfull, he can not denie himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe greate Searchers therefore that weigh the power of the aduerſaries by the ſtrength of theire humane forces and polecies, (wherein indeede they ſeeme to exceede vs) are like the tenne that ſearched <hi>Canaan,</hi> who diſhartened the people with a relation of the enemies ſtrength; ſo farre are they from <hi>Calebs</hi> faith and courage, who ſaw as much, and yet ſaide,
<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 13.28.</note> 
               <hi>let vs goe vp at once and poſeſſe it.</hi> For though as <hi>Moſes</hi> often ſaide, they were <hi>ſeauen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions greater and mightier then Iſrael,</hi> yet he knew that God had aſſured deſtruction to them, and victorie to his people. Such men therefore may doe well to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what Chriſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">w <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.8.</note> 
               <hi>the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnbeleeuing ſhall haue theire part in the lake.</hi> They conſider not that God doth commonly for his greater glorie ouercome the greateſt enemies by a power weaker in all humane reaſon then themſelues.
<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Beate therefore youre plow ſhares into ſwords, &amp; youre pruning hookes into ſpeares, let the weake ſay I am ſtronge,</hi> as the Prophet willeth; and let no man withhold them from this warre, fearing leſt they ſhould be defiled with blood, or thinking the iſſue will be doubtfull, and that therefore it would be better to perſwade to peace; which yet when he moſt would, he ſhall hardly longe obtaine from them that are gouerned by the Pope. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer (as Polibius ſaith)
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Polib. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 300</note> 
               <hi>If peace be iuſt and honest, it is a worthy poſſeſſion and most proffitable; but if it be diſhonourable and baſe, it is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20781:25"/>of all things most ſhamefull &amp; pernitious.</hi> Now if wee conſider how the caſe hath ſtood, and yet doth with our brethren the followers of Truth, yea and with the Truth it ſelfe, wee will then graunt what one proueth:
<note place="margin">B. Hall. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temp. on Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid and Achiſh.</note> viz. that <hi>the true Servants of God are in theire places, when they are in oppoſition to his enemies. Profeſſion of hoſtility becomes them better then leauges of amity.</hi> And indeede while Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ſeeke, or take peace of the Souldiers of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> they both make them thinke it is feare of theire ſtrength, and alſo ſo puffe them vp with conceite thereof, that as time ſerues they will be the more deſirous of warre, and all occaſions thereof. Yea, it cauſeth that while ſuch a peace laſteth, they will not ceaſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach, demaund, and obtaine either by flatteries or threats, till they may by peace get more to themſelues and theire religion, then they could haue donne by warre. Nor is it likely, that ſuch will longer hold it, then theire aduantage increaſeth therein.</p>
            <p>Neither is it alwaies ſufficient before God to ſay wee deſire peace; eſpetiallie where it is quarrell enough againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they haue the marke of the Beaſt, are the Souldiers of Antichriſt, and members of the greate whore, whoſe deſtruction is commanded. For as a famous Diuine <hi>ſaith,
<note place="margin">B. Hall. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temp. on the Gibeonites.</note> He that calls himſelfe the God of peace proclaims himſelfe the God of hosts: and not to fight where he hath commanded is to breake the peace with God, whiles wee nouriſh it with men.</hi> And who euer got by angring him to pleaſe others? or by looſing his fauour to get the momentarie, and vncertaine freindſhip of others? vncertaine I call it, becauſe God that hath iniurie thereby may therefore ſuffer it to be turned into deceite, hatred, and greater damage. That which men doe vniuſtly to preuent an euill, though it ſeeme greate polecie, is by Gods iuſt iudgement often turned into a cauſe that bringes the ſame euill vpon them, as appeareth Gen. 11.4. Iſa. 30.1.2.3. Ioh. 11.48. I know that in many places, cauſes &amp; times that place may verrie well be alleadged; <hi>If it be poſſible as much as in you lieth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.</note> liue peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with all men.</hi> But when God would that the whore ſhould be burned, and that the ſeauen Angels haue begunne to powre out theire vials full of the wrath of God; yea when theeſe things are alreadie in theire progreſſe, who is there, who if he be a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and Seruant of Chriſt will ſay that this, or the like place is congruently alleadged, betweene free Princes of ſo contrarie
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20781:26"/>Religions? to hearken is at that time better then ſacrifice, and Chriſt to be heard, Mat. 16.24.25.26. Ioh. 12. <hi>If any man ſerue me,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.25.26.</note> let him follow me, and where I am there ſhall alſo my Seruant be.</hi> If in warre, then with him, if in peace, then with him. When di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Kingdomes forſooke the Beaſt and whore, to follow the Word, it was ſaide, <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Christ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 11.</note> Since that time Chriſt, and they that follow him haue continually ſkirmiſhed againſt Antichriſt and his followers, and ſhould continue ſo doeing, till <hi>Rome</hi> and Antichriſt ſhould be deſtroyed, as is ſhewed Reuel. 14. chap. 15. chap. 16. &amp;c. And will Princes and States then that are his Leiftenants ſuffer the Beaſt and his to recouer or ſpoile any of theeſe Kingdoms, either by force or fraude? ſurely if they doe, thoſe Princes will condemne them, who with all theire might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and extend the dominion of Antichriſt: and ſo will they alſo who at the Popes becke led greate Armies to recouer Paleſtina: and that though God in Scripture require no ſuch thinge, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewes that it ſhall lie vnder the curſe till the reſtauration of the Iewes:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 11.15.</note> whereas he ſaith the contrarie of theeſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And yet the Ieſuits, Preiſts and other Papiſts goe aboute with the firebrands of errour and ſedition, that like <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes they may at leaſt ſpoile theeſe vines &amp; garnaries which are Gods, and not, as his foxes did, the enemies. Now they that are in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may know if they will that <hi>Chriſt</hi> our
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon had a vineard, he let it out vnto keepers;</hi> and that therefore they ſhould thinke of that,
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Take vs the foxes, the litle foxes that ſpoile the vines.</hi> Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially ſeeing theire cunning Preiſts are ſuch as the wonderwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dreamer, and falſe Prophet, of whome God ſaith,
<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.8.9. <hi>and chap.</hi> 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not conſent vnto him, nor hearken vnto him, neither ſhall thine eye pitie him, neither ſhalt thou conceale him. But thou ſhalt ſurely kill him.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 25.16.</note> Vexe the Madianites, and ſmite them for they trouble you with theire wiles:
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</note> I would they were cut off that trouble you.</hi> For theeſe indeede are <hi>the riuers and fountaines,</hi> through which the waters of errour, which come from the <hi>Romiſh Sea,</hi> are conueied into euery cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Land to the deſtruction of Soules. Theeſe fountaines and riuers are alſo, as it were the dougs, by which that Sea is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, as they by it. And indeede theeſe are they that venture to conuey floods of thoſe waters of errour and treaſon into thoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20781:26"/>Lands where Poperie is thruſt out, hopeing thereby to bringe people backe from the obedience of theire Princes, and indeede of Chriſt himſelfe vnto the obedience of the Pope theire Maiſter. For which they haue beene iuſtly puniſhed with death, as is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Reu. 16. <hi>The third Angel powred out his viall vpon the riuers and fountaines of waters, and they became blood.</hi> Which viall was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede powred out aboute the yeare 1581. when in <hi>England,</hi> it was ordained by publick authoritie, that all they that ſhould indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour by any meanes to draw the mindes of the ſubiects from theire obedience toward theire lawfull and naturall Prince to the Pope, or for that purpoſe ſhould draw them to theire religion, ſhould be put to death as traitors: the good example of which Edict was in ſome meaſure followed againſt the Ieſuits in other Kingdoms. And queſtionleſſe this is that which is ſignified by that viall. For indeede herein the Lord gaue them blood to drinke; becauſe they that brought theeſe waters of <hi>Rome,</hi> brought them with the danger of theire liues; and therefore they were not only turned to blood to thoſe that ſent them, nor only to blood in themſelues beeing apprehended; but alſo if they eſcaped a while to conuey them, they were alſo turned into blood to thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued them, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaide, of <hi>the water of Bethlehem,</hi> which the <hi>three mightie men</hi> fetched him through the <hi>host of the Philiſtines;
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.17.</note> is not this the blood of the men that went in Ieopardie of theire liues?</hi> Thus the righteous God gaue the Preiſts, and Ieſuits blood to drinke, who as wee know haue cauſed many good Chriſtians to be killed by the Inquiſition, and by animating Popiſh Princes to make warre againſt Proteſtants. This is that therefore vvhich the <hi>Angell</hi> of the waters ſaith there, <hi>Thou art righteous, ô LORD, which art, and wast and ſhall be, becauſe thou haſt iudged thus: for they haue ſhed the blood of Saints and Prophets, and thou hast giuen them blood to drinke, for they are worthy.</hi> If Gods <hi>Word</hi> ſay they be worthy, vvhat Chriſtian vvill pleade for them that ſuch lavves ſhould not be executed on them? Will they doe the like by vs?</p>
            <p>And therfore they who profeſſe themſelues Proteſtants, ſhould methinkes take heede, that they doe not ſo much as thinke that kinde of iuſtice to haue beene to ſeuere, and eſpetiallie that they diſſwade not from the execution of ſuch lawes, nor giue reaſons againſt them, leaſt they be thereby found to helpe the Beaſt, yea
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20781:27"/>to charge God of iniuſtice, and euen to diſpute againſt the holy Ghoſt, who by the Angell ſaith, <hi>they are worthy.</hi> Which that no man might once doubt <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith there, <hi>I heard another out of the Altar ſay, Euen ſo Lord God Almightie, true and righteous are thy iudgements.</hi> Thus then at leaſt the Romiſh Clergie are <hi>worthy.</hi> And the reſt haue the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>marke</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> Many of them fight his battailes, and haue ſought our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yea haue ſlaine many of our Brethren, and led many into captiuitie, as was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed Reuel. 13.10. therefore that ſhould be heard, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred which God there ſaith concerning euerie one of them, <hi>He that leadeth into captiuitie ſhall goe into captiuitie:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.10.</note> he that killeth with the ſword muſt be killed with the ſword.</hi> And indeede the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of them haue wiſhed our deſtruction, or ſubiection by the ſword, if not contributed to the effecting thereof; and thereby haue both made themſelues guiltie, and alſo giuen vs aſſured teſtimonie that this Scripture muſt ſhortlie be fulfilled in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of thoſe ſlaughters, and other diſaſters wrought by them. And all of them are members of that greate <hi>Whore,</hi> which ſitteth on many <hi>waters,</hi> and therefore are ſuch as thoſe of whome it is ſaide, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſeeke theire peace,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.6.</note> nor theire good all thy dayes for euer.</hi> God hath ſaide of the Whore ſitting on many wate s, <hi>Reward her as ſhe hath rewarded you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.6.</note> and double vnto her double according to her workes: in the cup which ſhe hath filled, fill to her double, &amp;c.</hi> and though he hath hereby principally deſigned the Citie of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet the Citie, or Woman is alſo to be conſidered as ſhe ſitteth on many <hi>waters, which are peoples, and multitudes and Nations.</hi> For whereas it is ſaide, <hi>The tenth part of the Citie fell;</hi> he doth not meane of <hi>Rome,</hi> as ſhe ſitteth on ſeauen mountaines, but <hi>on manie waters.</hi> From thoſe dayes, or rather from the time when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World are become the Kingdoms <hi>of our Lord, and of his Chriſt;</hi> the Whore and Antichriſt with her haue beene as a rotten, or ruinous howſe ready to fall.</p>
            <p>But the Ieſuits &amp; Preiſts haue obteined greate props to vphold her; which indeede are greate Kings, and Princes eſpetially the <hi>Kinge</hi> of Spaine; and howſe of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> Now that Proteſtant Prince which ſeeketh to weaken theeſe props, and pillars by an honourable warre, (as of late that noble Queene <hi>Elizabeth did</hi>) he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20781:27"/>without doubt doth a worke verrie acceptable to God, as tending to the Ruin of <hi>Rome</hi> and of Antichriſt, who otherwiſe can not be ouerthrowen: but if he ſpare the props, or ſtrengthen them, although he vainely hope thereby to ſtrengthen himſelfe (as they did Iſai. 30.2.) amonge whome will Chriſt our Captaine, and Iudge finde him? ſeeing he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.30.</note> 
               <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me ſcattereth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de peccator. meritis</hi> 18.</note> and as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nec est vlli vllus medius locus, vt poſſet eſſe niſi cum Diabolo, qui non eſt cum Christo. Neither is there any midle place for any man, that he can be with any other then the Diuell, who is not with Chriſt.</hi> Wee muſt not therefore doe ſuch a thinge vnder the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hope of doeing God the better ſeruice, as to his exceeding loſſe <hi>Saul</hi> did 1. Sam. 15. and likewiſe <hi>Ahab</hi> 1. King. 20.28.42. ſo dangerous a thinge it is for a man to make himſelfe wiſer then God. It is not therefore ſo ſmall a matter to neglect the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, and all the good that may come of this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, vnder euerie pretence.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture they who are otherwiſe affected will ſay, if to neglect this cauſe may be imputed to ſome for a fault; neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe there is no ſuch danger in it, if wee remember that Chriſt died for Sinners. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will anſwer them, <hi>That he died for all,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</note> that they which liue, ſhould not hence forth liue vnto themſelues, but vnto him which died for them, and roſe againe;</hi> and that muſt needes be, that as they ſhould therefore liue vnto him in other things, ſo in this alſo; eſpecially in ſuch times as theeſe, when the iniuries donne vnto the Church, and euen to the Truth himſelfe, ſeeme to require it of all that any way can giue helpe. Wee muſt not thinke that the members of Chriſt, who profeſſe and follow the Truth muſt alwaies ſuffer vnder Antichriſt, and his adherents; much leſſe Chriſt himſelfe, who is the Truth. For as wee may ſee Chriſt did many yeares agoe begin to conquer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 11.13.</note> when the <hi>tenth part</hi> of the <hi>citie fell,</hi> and the <hi>euerlaſting Gospell</hi> was alreadie begunne to be preached. For of thoſe times it is ſaide, <hi>feare God, and giue glory to him, for the howre of his iudgement is come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 14.6.</note> If it were come then in the time of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> how much more in theeſe our dayes who liue ſo many yeares after them? Let noe man now put off the time of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſeeing alſo of thoſe times it is ſaide for Gods honour, our comfort and theire terrour,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20781:28"/>
               <hi>Thou haſt taken vnto thee thy greate power,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>chap.</hi> 11.17.18.</note> and haſt raigned. And the nations were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead that they ſhould be iudged,</hi> (or reuenged) <hi>and that thou ſhouldest giue reward vnto thy Seruants the Prophets, and to the Saints, and to them that feare thy name, ſmall, and greate, and ſhouldst destroy them which deſtroy</hi> (or corrupt) <hi>the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.</note> Then <hi>the Temple of God was opened;</hi> and the ſeauen Angels come out with theire vials full of the wrath of God, as is ſhewed chap. 15. where
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>ſee chap.</hi> 15.5.6.</note> you may ſee that he commeth againe to this verrie time of the Temples ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, (mencioned chap. 11.) to ſhew what ſhould preſently follow; and that the iudging and deſtroying mencioned chap. 11.18. is meant of theeſe ſeauen vials <hi>full of the wrath of God,</hi> and which are the laſt plauges inflicted on Antichriſt and his followers, and other wicked men: and conſequently that from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Chriſt doth maintaine warre againſt the whore, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; and that not ſpiritually only, by the word, but euen vvith the verrie ſvvords of Princes, as may appeare from chap. 16. in diuers of thoſe ſeauen plauges, alſo chap. 17. verſ. 16. vvhere the Kings deſtroie <hi>Rome,</hi> vvhich muſt needes be one of the 7 plauges, becauſe theeſe ſeauen are the laſt plauges: it hath therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to many to be the ſift, becauſe that is poured on <hi>the throne</hi> or ſeate of <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> vvhich is <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet the vvarre is ſtill continued, chap. 19. vvhere vvee ſee that <hi>the armies</hi> called againſt Antichriſt are ſaide to <hi>follow</hi> Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>chap.</hi> 19.</note> vvho is theire Leader, or Generall.</p>
            <p>Is he then in the feild, and are vvee affraide to follovv him? or doe vvee thinke that all the vvarre is for a Kingdom not vvorth the labour? or vvhere the Generall beeing victour doth diuide no ſpoile amonge his follovvers? If it vvere ſo; yet methinkes vvhen Chriſt Ieſus is the <hi>Generall,</hi> there ſhould vvant no follovvers. The Popes Kingdom is of this vvorld, and therefore his follovvers fight for him, becauſe he giues them temporall revvards, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſpirituall, though indeede he can not performe promiſe. Chriſts Kingdom is not of this vvorld, therefore men fight not for him;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.36.</note> as he ſaith, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world: if my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were of this world, then would my Seruants fight.</hi> This he ſpake vvhen he vvas to ſuffer, and did not deſire that any ſhould fight to reſcue him. But novv (as you haue ſeene) he is to ſubdue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20781:28"/>enemies by the ſword, and therefore lookes for followers to fight, though his Kingdom be not of this World. Yet beſides ſpirituall honours and bleſſings, our Sauiour and Generall offers greate temporalites to his followers, vvhen he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.16.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall eate her fleſh;</hi> that is indeede her riches and reuenues: and againe, <hi>Come and gather youre ſelues together vnto the ſupper of the greate God</hi> (viz. vnto a feaſt, that he ſhould make them, as Iſa. 25.9.)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.17 18.</note> 
               <hi>That ye may eate the fleſh of Kings, and the fleſh of Captaines, and the fleſh of mightie men; &amp;c.</hi> that is indeede to take theire riches, pofeſſions and reuenues. Howſoeuer; the time beeing come, it will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſay, vvee are like to haue no pay;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.1.</note> or vvee haue not yet had any ſuch ſpeciall commandement to goe foorth. For vvithout doubt thoſe places of an
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Angel deſcending from heauen,</hi> of a
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>voice from heauen; of an
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.</note> Angell ſtanding in the Sunne,</hi> are not to be taken literallie: but in thoſe places is ſignified the voice of God in ſome Princes, Miniſters, or others ſtanding in the light and confidence of the truth: to theeſe other Seruants of Chriſt hearken, and are hereby ſaide,
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>to follow the Lambe witherſoeuer he goeth;</hi> and to be truly
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. de Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. par.</hi> 2. <hi>Theol. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trou. inter Scotum, &amp; Tho. cont.</hi> 20 <hi>act.</hi> 2. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Parcl. de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Pap. cap.</hi> 41. <hi>p.</hi> 341.</note> 
               <hi>called, and choſen and faithfull.</hi> The Papiſts boldly teach that,<hi rend="sup">f</hi> 
               <hi>Lice: praeceptum Praelati ſit irrationale, &amp; pro tale me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritò quand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que haberi potest, tenetur tamen ſubditus illud obſeruare:</hi> though the commandement of the ſuperiour be vnreaſonable, and may well enough be thought to be ſo, yet the inferiour is bound to obey it: that men are bound, <hi>Papae ſententiam exequi,</hi> to put the Popes ſentence in execution. And ſo wee perceiue the Ieſuits and Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts to go foorth, perſwading Princes &amp; people by diuers meanes to roote out the Proteſtants; and wee ſee them labouring what they can to do ſoe; ſo truly do they worſhip the beaſt, and his Image: and ſhall they then that are Chriſts, and pretend to loue him, be more afraide to doe the commandements of God in roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out them? eſpetially ſeeing that harlot is the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of ſoules. <hi>There is no feare in loue,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.18.</note> but perfect loue caſteth out feare: he that feareth is not made perfect in loue.</hi> Why then ſhould they feare? Doe they thinke that Chriſt will without theire la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour reuenge them? he can indeede, but his purpoſe is not ſo to doe, ſeeing he ſaith to them of the whore, which ſitteth on many waters, <hi>Reward her, as ſhe hath rewarded you, fill her double, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 18. <hi>Num.</hi> 25.17</note> As of old he ſaide, <hi>Vexe the Midianites, and ſmite them: for they vexe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20781:29"/>you with theire wiles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.17.</note> And as he ſaith, <hi>If ye know theeſe things, happy are ye, if ye do them. O daughter of Babylon who art to be destroyed: happy ſhall he be that rewardeth thee as thou haſt ſerued vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 137. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.24.</note> But as he ſaith, <hi>He that loueth me not kepeth not my ſayings.</hi> If therefore theeſe things be not donne, let vs not laie the fault on God; but rather ſay vnto him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.4.5</note> as pſa. 60. <hi>Thou haſt giuen a banner to them that feare thee, that it may be diſplaied becauſe of the truth. That thy beloued may be deliuered.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>pſa.</hi> 68.1.</note> Let God ariſe, let his enemies be ſcattered.</hi> The comfort is here, as Pſa. 110. <hi>The people ſhalbe willing in the day of thy power.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 110.3.</note> Faithfull is he that hath promiſed, who will alſo doe it.</hi> And though wee haue not beleeued,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tſm.</hi> 2.13</note> yet he <hi>abideth faithfull, he can not denie himſelfe.</hi> Theeſe things are indeede to be more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallie conſidered in theeſe laſt times of Antichriſt, wherein wee ſee or heare that our brethren haue beene in many places led captiue and ſlaine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.10.</note> as was propheſied Reu. 13.10. and that therefore wee are to expect with confidence that recompence which for our comfort is there aſſured to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. <hi>Here is the patience, and the faith of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20781:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
